<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative of the phanatical plot, setting forth the treasonable and wicked designs which they have been carrying on against the King &amp; government, ever since the last Westminster Parliament with an account of the treacherous contrivances against several worthy persons, and the measures which they used to take off the Kings evidence by subornation : to which is added a relation of the evil practices of John Rowse (who was lately executed at Tyburn), William Lewis (who stands convicted), and others / by John Zeale, Gent.</title>
            <author>Zeale, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Z10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21676</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12484257</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12484257</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62262)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 301:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative of the phanatical plot, setting forth the treasonable and wicked designs which they have been carrying on against the King &amp; government, ever since the last Westminster Parliament with an account of the treacherous contrivances against several worthy persons, and the measures which they used to take off the Kings evidence by subornation : to which is added a relation of the evil practices of John Rowse (who was lately executed at Tyburn), William Lewis (who stands convicted), and others / by John Zeale, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Zeale, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by most booksellers in Wetminster and London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rouse, John, d. 1683.</term>
               <term>Lewis, William, --  Gent.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62262:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62262:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE OF THE Phanatical Plot, Setting forth the TREASONABLE AND <hi>Wicked Deſigns</hi> Which they have been CARRYING on againſt the King &amp; Government Ever ſince the laſt <hi>Westminſter</hi> Parliament. WITH An Account of the <hi>Treacherous Contrivances</hi> againſt ſeveral Worthy Perſons, and the Meaſures which they uſed to take off the <hi>Kings Evidence</hi> by <hi>Subornation.</hi> To which is Added, A Relation of the Evil Practices of <hi>John Rowſe,</hi> (who was lately Executed at <hi>Tyburn</hi>) <hi>William Lewis</hi> (who ſtands Convicted) and others. By <hi>John Zeale</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold by moſt Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62262:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62262:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory TO TITUS OATES THE <hi>Mock-Doctor of Salamanca.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E find that it is Cuſtomary for the Bird of <hi>Jove</hi> to carry up her unfledg'd young ones to the <hi>Sun,</hi> where if they can with undaz'led eyes, behold the glittering Beams, all ſuſpicion of their being Spurious is taken away, After this example, with due reverence, I approach you, our <hi>Sun,</hi> and freely expoſe this off-ſpring of a penitent mind to your (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times) all-blinding Rayes; having a ſtock of aſſurance, equal to your own, when you deſcribed <hi>Don John;</hi> that if it can (what perſons of the greateſt quality formerly were not Eagles enough to do) without trembling behold your ſhining Caſe — hardn'd brow, it may paſs muſter all over the World, and mangre envy and mighty tydes of prejudiced <hi>Fanatical Criticks,</hi> ſet up for a Truth.</p>
            <p>And truly <hi>(Reverend Sir)</hi> I ſhould think it Incumbent on me, to be ſpeak your Pardon for troubling you at this time of day, with a thing of this nature, did not Juſtice and Reaſon, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſeem to warrant the preſumption: For though I muſt confeſs, I could not but ſuppoſe you as buſie as any of the <hi>Rats</hi> to free your
<pb facs="tcp:62262:3"/>ſelf from the danger that threatens your Drowning Veſſel, and to keep your Neck out of <hi>Jack Ketch</hi>'s Nooſe: Yet I thought (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being unjuſt to you and and my own Conſcience) I could not rob you of the Dedication of what in every line almoſt ſhews you your ſelf. <hi>Jupiter eſt quodcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vides,</hi> You can ſee nothing in it Dirty, Falſe, Black, Treaſonable or Treacherous, but it bears your own ſtamp: And though you cannot properly be ſaid to be the immediate Cauſe of all, yet the ſecond cauſes whence thoſe and all our National evils ſprang, can be reſolved into you, the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Mobile,</hi> or firſt Principle whence they had their being and motion.</p>
            <p>There is nothing contained in the following Diſcourſe but what, to your own knowledge, is purely matter of Fact, and an undeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Truth; which therefore I chooſe to expoſe to the World, in a ſtile ſuitably plain, naked, and deſtitute of the gawdy flowers of Eloquence and Invention, which makes the greatest Truths more Admired, but leſs Authentick, more deſired by curious and liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Palates, (ſuch as yours <hi>Doctor</hi>) but alſo more lyable to be ſuſpected by the more ſolid and judicious part of mankind, which alone I coveted, and have endeavoured to pleaſe. And I do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Religiouſly in the preſence of Him that knows all your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, and as I hope for any good in that day when there is to be the fulneſs of Retribution, that I was neither by aſſed by any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, nor moved by the Importunity of Friends, or the Threats of Foes, to write and publiſh the following <hi>Narrative;</hi> and that I can attribute the doing ſo to nothing, ſave an irreſiſtable impulſe within me, and the ſecret Dictates of a wounded Conſcience. The load of guilt that was lodg'd in my breaſt was inſupportable, and I could have no eaſe 'till I vomited up the Treaſonable Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natious, Briberies, Perjuries and Evil-practices which lay heavy on me, and to which for ſome years I have been privy, that at the ſight of ſo much filth the World may for the future nauſeate and abandon ſuch lewd and wicked extravagancies.</p>
            <p>I do not care for quarrelling with an old Friend, though the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; therefore I muſt beg, good <hi>Doctor,</hi> that you will not take up prejudice againſt me upon the firſt ſight of my <hi>Narrative;</hi> for, aſſure your ſelf, I deſign not thereby to encroach upon, or uſurp any part of your right: I mean, not thereby to aſſert a <hi>Popiſh,</hi> but a
<pb facs="tcp:62262:3"/>
               <hi>Presbyterian Plot.</hi> You are now without the fear of a Rival, left the ſole Maſter and mannager of the former; your leading <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> are all fled, and your Fellow-Swearers ſeeing all going down the wind, have ſhaken hands with you, committing all to your own unwearied care: You may then exerciſe your Talent in Swearing by your ſelf, and move in the ſame ſphear you uſed to do, 'till it ſhall pleaſe your juſter Stars to exalt you higher.</p>
            <p>Think not by what I have ſaid, that I am a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> aſſure your ſelf I am neither <hi>Papiſt</hi> nor <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> ſo far from it, that I never was within the doors of a <hi>Maſs-houſe</hi> or <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle,</hi> but was born and brought up in the True <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as Eſtabliſhed now by Law. To give an account of my Life in this place, I deem very unneceſſary; I'll therefore ſay thus much negatively concerning my ſelf; firſt, that I never took a Degree in <hi>Salamanca</hi> or elſewhere, which you are ſo much famous for. Secondly, that I never admired <hi>Sodomy,</hi> or ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my ſelf with a <hi>Maſculine Brawny</hi> Chamber-maid. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That I am not the Son of a Canting Sedition-Preaching <hi>Weaver,</hi> but of an Honeſt Loyal Gentleman of the County of <hi>Devon;</hi> and my Mother of the Family of the <hi>Greenfields,</hi> whoſe Loyalty have been always manifeſted by their Sufferings for His late Majeſty; My Grand-father periſhing in Priſon in <hi>London:</hi> My Uncle Major <hi>Greenfield</hi> Murdered by the Rebels at <hi>Plimouth,</hi> for endeavouring to obtain that Garriſon for His Majeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And moſt of my Relations falling into the Hands of the damnable Sequeſtrators, for which my ſelf and whole Family ſuffer to this day, further I will not mention to vindicate my ſelf, or to take away the ſtains which guilt left upon my Soul, for</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>Quae non fecimus ipſi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>vix ea noſtra voco</hi> —</l>
            </q>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>Plot;</hi> I dare not ſay there was no <hi>Popiſh-Plot,</hi> though at the ſame time it is my belief there was not the hundred part of what was pretended; but that the few true cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that were found, were improved to that height by your Induſtry, and the Treachery of the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> to ſerve for a ſtalking-horſe to hide your own, till with more ſecurity you
<pb facs="tcp:62262:4"/>could destroy the Government. Therefore I ll even reſt my ſelf ſatisfied as to this point, with the Opinion of the Author of that <hi>Letter to Mr.</hi> Settle, <hi>occaſioned by his Recanting Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> which you may ſee from his own words no fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.<note n="*" place="margin">Poſtſcript <hi>Page</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>As for the</hi> Popiſh-Plot, though my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of it are not altogether ſo dreadful to make me go mad for fear of Conſecrated Knives, Black-Bills, Jago-<hi>Pilgrims,</hi> French <hi>Armies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Yet I am not for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploding quite the thoughts of ſome Deſigns managed by the</hi> Roman Catholicks <hi>for promoting their own Religion, by extirpating all whom they call</hi> Hereticks, <hi>ſince there were many true circumſtances, though daſh'd with Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and now and then a few falſe Oaths. For we know very well 'tis poſſible the game may be up, though many of the Eager Mongrel Whelps in the deep mouth'd pack of Evidences out-run the ſcent and hunted Counter. But on the other hand, I would have men not be altogether ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent upon thoſe glowing Embers, as not to diſcern the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows</hi> (that is the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>) <hi>that blew them into a flame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may poſſibly be thought by ſome, that I dare not aſſert what I now do, but in the interval of Parliaments; and that this <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative,</hi> were it now Parliament time, dare not look abroad into the World: I declare my reſolution of ſtanding by it when ever a Parliament ſits; and (if need require) of ſealing the truth thereof with my Blood. For it was once my dying reſolution, and ſince I never found my ſelf in the leaſt inclining to alter it. In <hi>March</hi> laſt being juſtly viſited for my ſins with a ſevere ſit of Sickneſs from the Almighty, and having little or no hopes or proſpect of recovering, I ſent for a Friend, and made it my requeſt to him, that if it ſhould pleaſe God to call me away at that time, he would take care to have the following Diſcourſe Printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed for the ſatisfaction of the World, declaring to him upon the word of a dying man, that there was nothing in it, but what was ſincere and true; which he faithfully promiſed to ſee dome. But it pleaſing the all merciful God to raiſe me up once more to perform this great duty my ſelf; I think I ought not to be either aſhamed or afraid to declare thoſe notorious Truths before an
<pb facs="tcp:62262:4"/>Earthly which then I was willing, and expected, and at laſt muſt, lay open before the Heavenly Tribunal.</p>
            <p>And I hope the next Parliament will be men of greater, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler and more Loyal Principles than to diſcountenance any thing that may tend (as the detecting theſe Subornations, Perjuries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do) to the preſervation of His Majeſty, the Queen, and his Royal Highneſs, and to the bringing all Perjurers, Suborners, and other Enemies of the Government, to condign Puniſhment: Which time when God ſhall be pleaſed to grant us; <hi>Doctor</hi> you may expect to be Famous, as moſt that ever march'd through <hi>Holbourn:</hi> till which, I will, what you your ſelf muſt do at laſt leave you upon God and your Country, and ſo</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:62262:5"/>
            <head>A true and perfect Copy of the <hi>Records</hi> of <hi>Newgate</hi> againſt <hi>William Lewis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AT the General Seſſions of the Peace of our Lord the King,<note place="margin">Lond. ſſ.</note> held for the City of <hi>London</hi> at <hi>Guildhall</hi> of the ſame City, within the ſame City, on <hi>Monday, viz.</hi> the <hi>12th.</hi> day of <hi>December Anno Regni Regis Caroli ſecundi An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gli,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>28<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Lewis</hi> is Fined <hi>100</hi> l. and Committed <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that he ſhall be put in and upon the <hi>Pillory,</hi> one day in <hi>Cornhill</hi> near the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> and another day in the <hi>Poultry</hi> near the <hi>Stocks-Market</hi> there; and the third day in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near the end of <hi>Honey-Lane,</hi> from the hour of Eleven to One, With a Paper put on his Head in Writting ſhewing his Offence. And then he ſhall be returned to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> to be kept in ſafe Cuſtody until he has paid his Fine, and find good Security for his good Behaviour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The words which were put on his Head in the <hi>Pillory.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>For Falſly Forging a Bill under the Hand of Mr.</hi> Richard Thompſon <hi>to deceive him</hi> 220 l.</q>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <p>
               <hi>AT the Goal Delivery of our Lord the King at</hi> Newgate <hi>held for the City of</hi> London <hi>at</hi> Juſtice-Hall <hi>in the</hi> Old-Bayly London,<note place="margin">Lond. ſſ.</note> 
               <hi>on</hi> Wedneſday <hi>viz.</hi> 10th. of October, Anno Regni Regis <hi>Caroli</hi> Secundi nunc <hi>Angliae</hi> &amp;c. 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
            </p>
            <p>William Lewis <hi>Convicted of</hi> Fellony, <hi>and demands the</hi> Benefit of his Clergy, <hi>&amp;c. and is Delivered if he could read, which he did; and was only</hi> Burnt in the Hand, <hi>and ſo acquitted.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62262:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Villainy Diſplay'd:</hi> OR, THE INFORMATION OF John Zeale, Gent.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout the time that <hi>Langhorn</hi> was executed, I came acquainted with one <hi>Hugh Maſon,</hi> a Victualler in <hi>Strand-lane</hi> near the <hi>May-pole,</hi> whoſe Houſe I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards uſed; and one time telling him I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to be ſuborn'd to ſwear High-Treaſon againſt Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe,</hi> to whom I formerly was Page; and that Informations were ſent in my name to the Secretary of State, (neither my hand-writing, or by my conſent or knowledge) againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe,</hi> neither did I ever ſwear any matter againſt him: <hi>Maſon</hi> reply'd, <hi>Now is the time to make your ſelf, if you'll accuſe him, and I will draw up the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation againſt him; And more over, I'll warrant you a good ſum of money for ſo doing. Further,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I will carry you to Sir</hi> William Waller, <hi>Dr.</hi> Oates, <hi>and the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>who will all of them give you good encouragement, &amp;c.</hi> But finding me unwilling, <hi>Maſon</hi> for ſome time deſiſted his importunities, until (uſing his Houſe) I became ſomewhat indebted unto him; whereupon he told me, <hi>If I would not conſent to draw up an Information, and accuſe the ſaid Sir</hi> Francis Radcliffe <hi>of High-Treaſon, that he would arreſt me, and throw me into Priſon.</hi> Then I went to one Mr. <hi>Bennet</hi> a Sword-Cutler, (an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of my Fathers) and deſired him to go with me to the ſaid <hi>Maſon,</hi> and engage for what I was (or ſhould be) indebted, until my Father came to Town, which Mr. <hi>Bennet</hi> did at my requeſt. But before my acquaintance with <hi>Maſon,</hi> I had given Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe</hi> an account by one Mr. <hi>Banks,</hi> how I was perſuaded, and endeavoured to be ſuborn'd, and become an Evidence againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>Francis;</hi> Alſo I ſent a Letter to his Honour by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Banks,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62262:6"/>which was ſent me, directed (as I think) to my Lodging in <hi>Salisbury-Court,</hi> from an unknown hand, having no name to it. To the beſt of my remembrance, the words in the ſaid Letter were to this effect; <hi>to deſire me to accuſe Sir</hi> Francis Radcliffe <hi>of High-Treaſon, with promiſes of a gratuity;</hi> which Letter, I believe, remains ſtill in the hands of Sir <hi>Francis.</hi> And having cleared his Honour to Mr. <hi>Banks,</hi> I thought I might ſafely go on with the afore named <hi>Maſon,</hi> to find out his villanous intentions. One day he deſired me to go up ſtairs with him, which I did, and there again he urged me to draw up the ſaid Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation which he had endeavoured to Suborn me to do; all which I conſented unto: Then he immediately took Pen, Ink, and Paper, and began to draw up a Charge of High Treaſon againſt Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe;</hi> which Paper was not that day much proceeded upon, by reaſon of Company that came to his Houſe, which took him off his wicked deſign at that time: But ſome days after we proceeded fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the ſame buſineſs, ſo that at laſt we had finiſhed about a a ſheet of Paper containing all Treaſonable matter againſt Sir <hi>Srancis Radcliffe,</hi> all the particulars I cannot well remember; but one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular was, <hi>That Sir</hi> Francis Radcliffe <hi>ſhould have declared, that he would raiſe Ten Thouſand Men in Arms in the</hi> North <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>whereby to eſtabliſh the</hi> Popiſh Religion <hi>in this Kingdom:</hi> And during the time of this tranſaction, he the ſaid <hi>Maſon</hi> did daily report in his Houſe, that we were upon diſcovering a great Plot, which would be the making of Us that were concerned therein: And within a day or two after, he deſired me to go up Stairs with him again, <hi>And Dictate to him whilſt he drew up the ſaid Treaſonable Paper</hi> (which he had falſly contrived againſt Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe</hi>) <hi>in a more Legible Hand;</hi> which I did, and whilſt we were about it, the ſaid <hi>Maſon</hi>'s Wife came up ſtairs to us, at which he was diſpleas'd, and bad her go down; ſhe reply'd, <hi>I believe I ſhall ſee you in</hi> Newgate <hi>for your Plotting-contriving-tricks and Roguery;</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Damn you for a Bitch, how dare you talk ſo impudently to Doctor</hi> Oates <hi>and Captain</hi> Bedlow? (meaning himſelf and me;) And after this Treaſonable Paper of his contrivance was finiſh'd, <hi>Maſon</hi> would never let me reſt till I went with him to Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe</hi>'s Lodgings; I deſired to know of him what we ſhould do there? <hi>Damn you</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>we will ſhow him the Paper, and if does not give us Moneys, you ſhall Swear againſt him:</hi> Accordingly I did go with him into <hi>Holbourn,</hi> and there ſent for one Mr. <hi>Selby,</hi> Steward to Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> who immediately came to us; I call'd him into the Back-ſide, and told him, that I had the Copy of the Treaſon, which <hi>Maſon</hi> endeavoured to Suborn me to Swear againſt his Maſter Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe;</hi> he deſired to ſee it, but I am not certain whether I did let him ſee it, or not; but <hi>Maſon</hi> would not let me ſend it over to Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> but go with it my ſelf; at which Mr. <hi>Selby</hi> went over, telling me, he would ſend for me im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately; and when he was gone, the ſaid <hi>Maſon</hi> Swore he would go over with me; I ask'd him for what? <hi>Why</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to ſee Sir</hi> Francis, <hi>that I may know him, for by God</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>if he does not give
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62262:6"/>you Money, we will both Swear againſt him:</hi> But notwithſtanding his readineſs, I did not ſuffer him to go over, but went my ſelf, and ſent the ſaid Treaſonable Paper up to Sir <hi>Francis</hi> by one Mr. <hi>Radcliffe</hi> Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s Kinſman; I tarry'd there for ſome time, till near night, there being in company one Mr. <hi>Nichols</hi> a Taylor to Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> who came to take his leave of that Family, being with few days to go out of Town: And drinking a Glaſs of Wine with them, I declar'd before the whole Company, that I knew no ill of Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> but that it was a contriv'd and deſign'd thing by ſome ill perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to put me upon the Swearing the ſame: Upon which, after ſome ſhort ſtay, I took leave, and went to ſee for <hi>Maſon</hi> at the Alehouſe where I left him; but he being gone from thence, I repaired to his Houſe; who ſaid (as ſoon as he ſaw me) <hi>I am glad you are come Mr.</hi> Zeal, <hi>I had thought they had Murthered you, becauſe you tarryed ſo long; But that's not the buſineſs, have you gotten any Money from Sir</hi> Francis? ſaid he; I reply'd, I had not, for his Honour was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged with ſeveral Perſons of Quality that came to take their leaves of him before he went out of Town, which prevented me from ſpeaking with him at that time, but was ordered by Mr. <hi>Radcliffe</hi> his Kinſman to come again before Sir <hi>Francis</hi> took his Journey into the <hi>North;</hi> ſaid <hi>Maſon, That's very well, we will be ſure to mind him; and if he goes out of Town and not give you a good Gratuity, we will fetch him back in the Devils name:</hi> Thus it continued for ſome days, until Sir <hi>Francis</hi> was gone his Journey; and I hearing of it, told <hi>Maſon</hi> the ſame; who ſwore bitterly, <hi>That he would have him back in few days, if I would be ruled by him, and go immediately to Sir</hi> William Waller, <hi>and be ſworn to the ſaid Paper:</hi> But I put him off with ſome pretence or other for that time; telling him, that it would look more like malice than matter of Fact, to accuſe Sir <hi>Francis</hi> ſo ſoon after his departure.</p>
            <p>In a ſhort time after my Father came to Town, which was about St. <hi>James</hi>'s-<hi>Tide</hi> in the ſame Summer, and paid the ſaid <hi>Maſon</hi> what I was Indebted unto him; upon which, <hi>Maſon</hi> deſiſted from urging me to Swear againſt Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe;</hi> until about <hi>Michaelmaſs</hi> following, I then became Indebted to him a ſecond time, my Father having left his Houſe, finding him to be an Ill-principl'd man; my Father telling me, that was the cauſe that he refrain'd the ſaid <hi>Maſon</hi>'s Houſe; <hi>Maſon</hi> perceiving the ſame, was much diſſatisfied, telling me, that now I muſt look to my ſelf, <hi>For</hi> (<hi>Damn me</hi> ſaith he) <hi>I'le not truſt you for a Farthing more, beſides I will Arreſt you for what you owe me already too:</hi> Upon which I ask'd him what he would have me to do? <hi>Why</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>go with me to Doctor</hi> Oates, <hi>and I will give him the Paper, and tell him that I have one that will Swear to it; at which</hi> (ſaid <hi>Maſon</hi>) <hi>you will be call'd into the Doctor, but do not be ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous</hi> (ſaid <hi>Maſon</hi>) <hi>and diſgrace me, but ſtand to it, and Swear it, and then it will be your making:</hi> And ſeeing him ſo forward, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to go with him to <hi>Whitehall</hi> to Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Lodging, to whom <hi>Maſon</hi> gave the ſaid Treaſonable Paper that he contriv'd againſt Sir
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62262:7"/>
               <hi>Francis Radcliffe;</hi> which the <hi>Doctor</hi> had no ſooner read, but ask'd if I was the perſon that would <hi>Swear</hi> to it? to which <hi>Maſon</hi> reply'd, I was, Then ſaid the <hi>Doctor,</hi> go with me to the <hi>Council-Chamber,</hi> and I will ſhew it to a Perſon of Quality: And as ſoon as we came into the <hi>Lobby</hi> by the <hi>Council-Chamber,</hi> the <hi>Doctor</hi> ſent in, and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> came out, and the <hi>Doctor</hi> gave him the Paper, which his Lordſhip read, and going towards his Coach at <hi>Whitehall-gate,</hi> his Lordſhip ask'd where the perſon was that would Swear to it? to which the <hi>Doctor</hi> reply'd, <hi>He's here my Lord;</hi> and then the <hi>Doctor</hi> recommended me to his Lordſhip, his Honour being pleaſed to deſire me to come in the Afternoon to his Houſe in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet,</hi> where he would diſcourſe me; upon which I promiſed his Lordſhip I would, and ſo took leave, and the <hi>Doctor</hi> bad me not fail to go according to his Lordſhips appointment, whatever I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected elſe; further telling me, I might be made by it: I promiſed I would certainly be there; (<hi>Maſon</hi> all this while ſtanding at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) I went to him, who asked me how it went? I told him the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> deſired me to come to his Houſe in the Afternoon, and there he would diſcourſe me; upon which <hi>Maſon</hi> was very well ſatisfied, and Swore, <hi>Damn him, that if I did mind my buſineſs, I ſhould be made for ever:</hi> After which, we went to his Houſe, where we had a Dinner, and there he told his Wiſe (with great rejoycing) that we had done our buſineſs, <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>We have been with the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>and Doctor</hi> Oates, <hi>and in the Afternoon Mr.</hi> Zeale <hi>muſt attend his Lordſhip at his Houſe by his own order:</hi> Towards the evening I went to his Lordſhip's Houſe, but <hi>Maſon</hi> could not go with me, by reaſon of ſome extraordinary occaſions of his own that hindred him; and coming to his Lordſhips Houſe, I had not been long there, but Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> and Collonel <hi>Manſel</hi> came in; the <hi>Doctor</hi> ſeeing me, went in to his Lordſhip as I imagine, and ſoon after came out to me, and told me his Lordſhip was very buſie, <hi>And therefore</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I would have you come again a day or two hence, and then you'l be ſure to ſpeak with my Lord;</hi> But (ſaid Doctor <hi>Oates</hi>) <hi>cannot you get one more that was of Sir</hi> Francis Radcliffe<hi>'s Family to Swear to the ſaid Paper?</hi> I told him, I thought I could, (though really I could not;) He reply'd, <hi>If you could do that, it would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Service;</hi> And ſo I took leave of him, and repaired again to <hi>Maſon</hi>'s Houſe, who was very earneſt to know how I had proceeded, I told him I could not ſpeak with the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> for Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſaid to me, he had ſo much company with him, that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to ſpeak with his Lordſhip that evening, deſiring me to come a day or two hence; at which <hi>Maſon</hi> ſwore <hi>Damn him, he believed I had received Money of his Lordſhip, and would not tell him:</hi> Upon which, I proteſted to him I had not, but muſt attend a day or two hence: He not believing it, ſaid, <hi>I will ſee the truth of this, for I will go with you my ſelf:</hi> I reply'd, with all my heart; and the <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following we both went into <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet;</hi> and coming to his Lordſhips Houſe, he was not within; ſo we went to an Ale-houſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62262:7"/>hard by, and tarried till we underſtood his Lordſhip was come in, when going to his Houſe, I ſent up my name, and was immediately conducted into his Lordſhips preſence up one pair of ſtairs, where he ask'd me ſeveral queſtions, <hi>(viz.) What Religion I was of?</hi> I anſwer'd, a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> He alſo ask'd me, <hi>What Friends I had in Town?</hi> I told him, <hi>my Father;</hi> To which his Lordſhip reply'd, <hi>bring him to me, and then I will diſcourſe You further.</hi> After which I took my leave, and was conducted down ſtairs by a Gentleman, (<hi>Maſon</hi> ſtanding all the while at the Chamber-door, and ſeeing me diſcourſe with his Lordſhip.) When we came out of the Houſe, <hi>Maſon</hi> asked me <hi>what News?</hi> I told him, his Lordſhip had order'd me to bring my Father to him; He reply'd, <hi>I will perſwade your Father to go with you, and will tell him, that you will have twenty Guineys of the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury; <hi>and this</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>will certainly induce him to go with you.</hi> Being come to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Houſe, he there openly declar'd we had been at the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s, and that I was lighted up ſtairs to his Lordſhip, as if I had been a Perſon of Quality, and he would warrant I ſhould have Money plenty as ſoon as I was ſworn; telling his Wife, that he would have his Room two pair of ſtairs hang'd for me, and that I ſhould both Lodge and Dyet in his Houſe, (or words to that effect.) This being <hi>Saturday</hi>-night, we deſiſted until <hi>Monday</hi> following, when we both went over towards my Fathers Lodgings near St. <hi>George's Fields;</hi> and as we went along, he told me, that after I had begun with Sir Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe,</hi> I ſhould accuſe the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and the Lords in the <hi>Tower; and</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>let me alone to contrive and draw up ſuch Informations againſt them, as ſhall bring you into great favour with the next Parliament,</hi> or words to that effect; So drawing near my Fathers Lodgings, <hi>Maſon</hi> deſired me to walk in the Fields, whilſt he went in and diſcourſed my Father; which I did, (but whether I went in or not, I cannot well remember;) however, <hi>Maſon</hi> tarry'd a conſiderable time with him, as he informed me, though I judg'd he would have but an indifferent anſwer to what he propoſed. At length he came, and told me, my Father had promiſed to be at his Houſe that day, or ſpeedily after; that being all the diſcourſe we had at that time, we parted, I going towards <hi>London,</hi> and he towards his own Houſe. Some days after I ſaw my Father, who ask'd me what was the reaſon I ſent that fellow to him (naming <hi>Maſon</hi>) upon ſuch accounts as he offered? telling me moreover, that if I did not refrain <hi>Maſon</hi>'s company, and evil practices, he would never look upon me. <hi>Maſon,</hi> (ſaid my Father,) was ſo impudent, in the hearing of my Landlady, to deſire me to perſwade you to ſwear againſt Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe;</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me you ſhould have Twenty Guineys of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> as ſoon as you are ſworn. In anſwer to all which, I told my Father, that I had left the ſaid <hi>Maſon</hi>'s houſe, and alſo refrained his company, which in truth I had done. And this (to the beſt of my knowledge) was the ſole contrivance of the ſaid <hi>Maſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62262:8"/>
            <p>All the before-mentioned Information I had drawn up againſt the ſaid <hi>Maſon,</hi> with an intent to have diſcovered it during the ſitting of the laſt Parliament, but was perſwaded to the contrary by one Mr. <hi>William Lewis,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>John Haytor,</hi> (then both Priſoners in the <hi>Marſhalſea</hi> for Debt, as well as my ſelf) who both told me, tho' the thing was really true, and that <hi>Maſon</hi> had endeavoured to ſuborn me, yet the Parliament would take no notice of it, becauſe it was in vindication of a <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> whereupon I burnt the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and deſiſted until now; only I declared in general to Juſtice <hi>Rich</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Reading</hi> above two years ſince, that <hi>Maſon</hi> had endeavoured to ſuborn me, but did not declare to them in what nature or particular.</p>
            <p>About <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> following, my Father had a Warrant granted him to be Purſer to one of His Majeſty's Ships at <hi>Chatham,</hi> to which Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment he repaired, and took me down with him, where I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for ſome months; but having no likelyhood of getting any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment there, and hearing of the Earl of <hi>Oſſory</hi>'s going as General for <hi>Tangier,</hi> I got leave of my Father to go to <hi>London,</hi> and make what intereſt I could to go with his Honour in that Expedition, and thereby endeavour to raiſe my Fortune, there being no probability of Action here: To which my Father conſenting, I accordingly came to Town about the latter-end of <hi>June,</hi> or beginning of <hi>July;</hi> but I had not been long here, e'r the ill News of the Earl of <hi>Oſſory</hi>'s death was generally confirmed, which put me to as great a loſs as ever; for having contracted ſome Debts, I was arreſted for the ſame, and thrown into the <hi>Marſhalſea,</hi> where I became acquainted with the before-mentioned Mr. <hi>William Lewis,</hi> who underſtanding how I had been tamper'd with to ſwear High-Treaſon againſt Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe,</hi> and had been with the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> concerning the ſame, he was very deſirous to be my Bed-fellow, which in a night or two he accompliſhed, and continued in my Room till his enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In few nights after he came to be my Bed-fellow, he began to tamper with me concerning the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> telling me, if I would accuſe his Lordſhip, he would ſend to thoſe that ſhould ſoon procure my liberty, and alſo ſupply me with Moneys; in which time I found him to be a notorious <hi>Papiſt;</hi> yet, through his many perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, I did conſent to the drawing up of an Information againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> whereupon one morning the ſaid <hi>Lewis</hi> came to my bed-ſide, and brought me Pen, Ink and Paper, deſiring me to draw up an Information according to my own ſenſe againſt the ſaid Earl; which I accordingly did, containing one ſide of a ſheet; and when it was done, he deſired to ſee it; I gave it him; he read it, and told me it all ſignify'd nothing; <hi>But</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I will go and draw it up in another kind of method, and you ſhall copy it with your own hand; for</hi> (ſaid Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>) <hi>I have ſent for a Gentlewoman to come to me, and have aſſured her in my Letter, that there is a Gentleman my (Bed-fellow) that can diſcover ſtrange things againſt the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury; <hi>and I am certain as ſoon as ſhe receives my Letter, ſhe will come with all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62262:8"/>to us: Therefore</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>let us make what ſpeed we can to get it ready;</hi> which accordingly we did. Within a day or two after, there came two women, and a Foot-boy with them, and enquired for him, (as he told me.) When they were gone, I ask'd him who they were? he ſaid, one of them was Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and the other Madam <hi>Holeby;</hi> and not long after there came a Gentlewoman, (which proved to be the ſaid Madam <hi>Holeby</hi>) who deſired to have it atteſted under my hand, that the Paper that was given to them againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> at their laſt being there, was true; deſiring me alſo to give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my hand that I would ſwear to it; all which Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me to do, and I did give under my hand that I would ſwear it. Then Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> told me we ſhould ſoon be releaſed out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and not long after the ſaid Paper came with an addition to it, and written by another hand, being brought by one Mr. <hi>Dalton.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> then deſired me to draw it up with my own hand as fair as I could: I reply'd, there was a great deal more ſtuff in that, than was in the other which was ſent them: <hi>Lewis</hi> anſwer'd, <hi>That's no matter, as long as it is for our enlargements;</hi> by which perſwaſions I at length conſented. As ſoon as it was done, Mr <hi>Dalton</hi> came for it, and took it away; but not long after he brought it again, and told me I muſt ſet my hand to the bottom of every ſide, which I did. Some weeks after, this contriv'd Paper was ſent to the Secretary of State, (as I afterwards heard) without my knowledge or conſent; whereupon Mr. <hi>Fanſhaw,</hi> one of the Maſters of Requeſts, and another perſon with him, came to the <hi>Marſhalſea,</hi> and enquired for me; when I came to him, he deſired me to go up with him into a Room, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I went; (which Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> perceiving, and being jealous, (as he afterwards told me) came under the window, and liſtened to our diſcourſe.) Mr. <hi>Fanſhaw</hi> pull'd the ſaid Paper out of his pocket, and deſired to know of me if it was my hand, or whether I would own it; I told him I would, and would alſo ſwear it when I ſhould be thereunto required; upon which he departed; and when they were gone, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> came to me and told me in theſe words; <hi>Now Mr.</hi> Zeal <hi>I dare trust my life in your hands, for I find you are true to your Trust;</hi> further telling me, that he heard every word that paſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Mr. <hi>Fanſhaw</hi> and my ſelf; the next news I heard, came a <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger</hi> with an Order of Council for me to be brought up the <hi>Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following, which was accordingly done; but I was not call'd in at that time, but ordered to be brought up the next Council day, and ſo I was carried up five ſeveral times; And being brought back from the Council un-examined, <hi>Lewis</hi> urged me to ſwear to the ſaid Paper, taking a Glaſs of Beer and drinking to me, wiſh'd eternal damnation both to Soul and Body, if he did believe the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to be in the leaſt concerned in any contrivance againſt the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Government,</hi> but that he did believe it to be a contrivance of the Earl of <hi>Shaftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> and others, on purpoſe to bring His Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into diſlke with the People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the laſt time I was carried up, I writ in to the Lord <hi>Precedent,</hi> declaring that it was the fifth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62262:9"/>time I had attended there, but could not be examined, and therefore deſired his Lordſhip that I might be call'd in and examined, ſo that I might diſcharge my Conſcience in declaring the truth of what I then knew, and if I had been then admitted I had declared Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s evil Practices in what I knew at that time; which Note I Writ to his Lordſhip in the preſence of Mr. <hi>Glover</hi> (now Marſhal of the <hi>Kings-Bench;</hi>) And about this ſaid time there came a perſon to Mr. <hi>Thomas Warens</hi> the Clerk of the <hi>Marſhalſea,</hi> and ſent for Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> who went out, and when he returned, he told me it was Madam <hi>Holeby</hi> that ſent for him, and that ſhe had given him five Shillings for us to drink; withall told me, I ſhould not tarry a day in Priſon. The ſaid Mr. <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis</hi> would never leave me night nor day, but was ſtill urging me to ſtand to it, and not to be daunted, but aver it to be truth when I came before the Council; he did alſo offer to inſtruct me againſt I came to be examined, ſaying one night in the Bed to me, <hi>come Mr.</hi> Zeal, <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I now was Lord Chancellor, and you before the King and Council to be examined. What do you know againſt the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury? Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I pretended my ſelf ſleepy, and would not anſwer him to any ſuch impertinent queſtions; Then he ſaid I would not remember three words of the ſaid Papers; (which I never intended) but the firſt time that I ſhould be examined, I reſolved to declare the Authors of the ſaid Papers; and that it was all falſe and fictitious, which I did declare upon Oath before the King and Council, the Lord Mayors day at night, during the laſt <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> but Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired me not to declare that he had any hand in contriving the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> which at that time I omitted; But now declare that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> was the firſt and chiefeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver and actor in it, and the only man that perſwaded me continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſwear to it: And when the Parliament ſat at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> he found that Mrs. <hi>Celiers</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Holeby</hi> did not ſupply him with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys as he expected, he reſolved to lay the contrivance of the ſaid Paper wholly upon them, which he did, as appears in his <hi>Narrative,</hi> and at that time I was much indiſpos'd, and told one Sir <hi>Edward Butler</hi> (a fellow Priſoner for Debt, and then in my Chamber,) that Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> was an ill man, and endeavoured to Suborn me to ſwear falſe things, and if I knew how to ſend for a Magiſtrate or two, I would declare the truth of what I knew: to which the ſaid Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> told me, that he would ſet down the day of the month, and what I had told him concerning Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and that he would juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the ſame upon Oath if ever required; And Sir <hi>Edward Butler</hi> alſo deſired me to write to ſome Juſtices of the Peace, to come thither, and take my Information, which I did; and ſoon after came one or two Juſtices, but Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> and Mr. <hi>Haytor</hi> being in conſultation in <hi>Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> Chamber, and underſtanding what I had done, they came down, and told the ſaid Juſtices it would not be a proper buſineſs for them to concern themſelves in, there being ſome Members of Parliament appointed to come and take my Examination; and Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> and Mr. <hi>Haytor</hi> deſired me not to declare one word to the ſaid Juſtices;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62262:9"/>upon which they took their leaves, and look'd upon it as an affront; (as I was inform'd;) and that night came other Juſtices and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> and Mr. <hi>Haytor,</hi> who told me he was by: This ſaid <hi>Haytor</hi> was him that writ Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Information and mine, that we gave in to the laſt <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and the next day came Juſtice <hi>Rich</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Reading,</hi> and took my Information alſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath; and after they were gone, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> told me, that (now Mr. <hi>Zeale</hi>) we may expect to be call'd before the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> ſpeedily; This continued for ſeveral days, inſomuch that Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> began to doubt whether there would be any notice taken of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, or not; And one Morning about three of the clock he wak'd me, and ſaid <hi>Zeale, here is no notice taken of us you ſee, but in every days Votes of</hi> Parliament <hi>there is Addreſses made for</hi> Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, <hi>and others, for their Pardons and Allowances; Therefore I muſt diſcover ſomething that is greater, or elſe we are like here to continue;</hi> I ask'd how or what he would contrive? <hi>let me alone for that,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you ſhall go in the Morning betimes to Mr.</hi> Haytors <hi>Chamber, and tell him that I did diſcover to you ſtrange things about three of the clock, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that I would not let you reſt until I had revealed it;</hi> But (ſaid he) <hi>take no notice that I know of your going to</hi> Haytor, <hi>but pretend you came unknown to me, and then</hi> (ſaid he) Haytor <hi>will certainly write to the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>immediately after you have told him what I can diſcover;</hi> Then I ask'd him again what it ſhould be? He replyed, <hi>that one of the Lords in the</hi> Tower <hi>would have hired him to have kill'd the King:</hi> I ask'd him what Lord it ſhould be? He replyed, <hi>do not you tell</hi> Haytor <hi>his name, but it ſhall be the Lord</hi> Arrundel of Warder, <hi>for he is the remarkable'st man of them all, he's ſquint-ey'd, and hath a Wart on his Noſe, and I have ſeen him ſeveral times at the</hi> Tennis-Court, <hi>therefore he ſhall be the man that I pitch upon, and I'l warrant you, this will fetch me up before either the Houſe of</hi> Lords <hi>or</hi> Commons; <hi>if</hi> Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>ſhould ask you why I had not diſcovered this before in my firſt Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, tell him, (to ſham him,) that I doubted my Pardon, and that was the reaſon, which will ſatisfy him well enough to believe it's true;</hi> And in the Morning I did riſe, and go to <hi>Haytors</hi> Chamber, and told him as aforeſaid, not taking the leaſt notice to him that the ſaid diſcovery was falſe, and contrived by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lewis;</hi> upon which the ſaid <hi>Haytor</hi> replyed, <hi>that he doubted the truth of it, yet notwithſtanding</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I will write to the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>of it, ſo it will be a good ſervice to the</hi> Proteſtant Party; the ſaid <hi>Haytor</hi> did accordingly write to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> concerning the ſame, and ſoon after there came an Order from the Houſe of <hi>Lords</hi> for Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> to be brought up; which accordingly he was, whereas he told me he ſwore the ſame; and withal at the ſame time ſwore, <hi>Damn him, what was an Oath? It was only laying a mans Hand on a Book and kiſſing it;</hi> upon all which, I have taken the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> according to the uſage of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the fourth day of <hi>February</hi> laſt, as will appear by my Certifitate, that all this is falſe and Fictitious, and contrived on purpoſe to get his enlargement. Some time after he was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62262:10"/>called before the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> where he delivered his Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in writing, and the 19th. of <hi>November</hi> I alſo delivered my Info<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rmation in writing; And within few days after he ſold his <hi>Narrative</hi> to one Mr. <hi>Combs</hi> a <hi>Coffee-man</hi> in the City for 50 <hi>l.</hi> which money, (or part of which) procured his Liberty. I remaining ſtill a Priſoner till near <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and upon the 5th. of <hi>November</hi> there came a Letter to the <hi>Marſhalſeas</hi> directed to Mr. <hi>Loman</hi> the Keeper, which is here incerted <hi>verbatim.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THere is this day an Order of the Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Zeale</hi> attend the <hi>Attorney-General,</hi> ſo he deſires that he may attend him in the Morning at the Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> or in the Afternoon before three, at his Chamber in <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> deſiring you not to fail, herein I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> 
                        <date>the <hi>25</hi> of <hi>November.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>You Servant <hi>Charles Clare.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>In Obedience to which Order I did appear at the <hi>Attorney-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi>'s Chamber, where he was pleas'd to ask me whether I knew Mrs. <hi>Celier?</hi> which I declared I did not; he ask'd me if I thought I knew her if I ſaw her, from any other Woman; I told him I could not ſay it for the World; and ſeveral other queſtions he was pleas'd to ask me relating to the ſaid matter, which I to the beſt of my knowledge truly anſwered: He alſo ask'd if I ever were in <hi>Newgate?</hi> I reply'd I was; he deſired me to give him an account for what; I told him; I was introduc'd by a Gentleman of my acquaintance, into the company and acquaintance of Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> who told me he was an Officer lately come from <hi>Flanders;</hi> and being one day in the company of Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> at <hi>Hackney,</hi> where he exchang'd a falſe <hi>Guiney,</hi> and for which he was apprehended, and I (with the ſaid Gentleman) was alſo apprehended with him for being in his company at that time; and being all carried before a Magiſtrate, all three were committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where in few days it appeared, that the ſaid <hi>Dangerfield</hi> made it his general practice to utter falſe Coyn for ſeveral years before, for which he had been ſeveral times Impriſoned, and ſuffered the Law: and during my confinement I writ to Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundbury Godfrey,</hi> declaring my condition, (who was my very good Friend, as I can very plainly prove,) he came to me in Priſon, to whom I declared my condition, upon which he was pleaſed to give me ſome Money, and told me withal, that if I could procure Bail, he would ſend me my Diſcharge; which I did do, and he accordingly ſent it me by a Gentleman; (a Friend of mine) and my Friends not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in Town to ſupply me with Moneys, I was forc'd to tarry till the Seſſions, becauſe I had not wherewithal to pay my Fees; at the Seſſions following I was Indicted for <hi>High Treaſon</hi> with Mr. <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> of which I was acquitted; and at the ſame time was alſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted for a miſdemeanour with <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> of which I was found,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62262:10"/>
               <hi>Guilty,</hi> and Fined Twenty Pounds Sterling, and <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was Fined Fifty Pounds: After my Tryal, Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi> was pleaſed to come to me to the <hi>Preſs-yard,</hi> and told me, <hi>That he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared upon the</hi> Bench <hi>in my behalf, and that he had ſpoke favourably of me to the then</hi> Recorder Dalbin: Beſides Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi> was alſo pleaſed to tell me, <hi>That he had ſaved my Friend</hi> Dangerfield <hi>from ſtanding in the</hi> Pillory <hi>for that Offence, in ſpeaking well of me;</hi> And afterwards Captain <hi>Richardſon</hi> the Keeper, having received a Letter frome one Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> to deſire him to be kind to me during my Confinement, I being of an Honeſt good Family, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> telling him alſo what kindneſs he ſhewed to me, he would take it as done to himſelf for my Families ſake, or words to that effect: Upon which, Captain <hi>Richardſon</hi> was ſo kind as to get my Fine remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Kings moſt Gracious Pardon, and alſo took my own engagement for my Fees, Lodging, and other Subſiſtance; at which the <hi>Attorney-General</hi> was pleaſed to tell me, that my Evidence was good by vertue of the Kings General Pardon if I never had ſuffered for any other Crimes, which I declared I never had; then his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ask'd Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> whether he had ever ſtood on the Pillory, or not; Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> changing his Countenance, reply'd, he had; Mr. <hi>Attorney-General</hi> alſo ask'd him for what? He anſwered, that it was for a Forg'd Bill of Exchange; ſome other ſuch like queſtions were ask'd him, which I cannot well remember; all this was in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of one Mr. <hi>Beal</hi> a Meſſenger belonging to the <hi>Marſhalſeas,</hi> who was at that that time my Keeper: From thence I return'd back to the ſaid <hi>Priſon,</hi> where I told the before-mentioned <hi>Haytor</hi> what had paſſed before Mr. <hi>Attorney-General</hi> that Afternoon, and how Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> had confeſſed that he had ſtood on the Pillory: Then <hi>Haytor</hi> reply'd, that he took him to be a very ill man ever ſince he writ his Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, for which he promiſed him a Beaver-Hat: <hi>But</hi> (ſaid <hi>Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>) <hi>He was ſo dirty as to go away and not perform his Promiſe, nor ſo much as return me Thanks for the ſame; but</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I will do him as good a kindneſs to the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>which ſhall be more than ten ſuch Hats out of his way: And on the other ſide, (if you'l be rul'd by me) I will make your Intereſt great with his Lordſhip:</hi> I ask'd him how, or which way? He told me, <hi>That he would make an Addition to my Narrative that it ſhould far exceed Mr.</hi> Lewis<hi>'s:</hi> And finding his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, I promiſed I would; then <hi>Haytor</hi> deſired me to inſert in Informations, and Swear to it, <hi>That the</hi> King <hi>would have ſeized the City-Treaſury by force of Arms; and that the Earl of</hi> Feverſham <hi>was the Perſon deſigned to command the Guards to effect the ſame:</hi> He alſo told me, <hi>That if I would publiſh the ſame, it would be the only means that he knew to Incenſe the Parliament againſt the</hi> King, <hi>ſo that they ſhould not conſent to give His Majeſty any Moneys until he had ſigned the</hi> Bill of Excluſion <hi>againſt the Duke of</hi> York: I reply'd, I had no Order for the Printing my Informations: <hi>Oh,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>let me alone for that, I will engage the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>to get you an Order as ſoon as he underſtands by me what great conſequence you have to diſcover:</hi> He the ſaid <hi>Haytor</hi> further declaring, <hi>That his Lordſhip had a great influence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62262:11"/>upon the</hi> Houſe of Commons, <hi>who were rul'd much by his perſwaſions, and that nothing of Moneys would ever be granted by them to the King, until the Duke of</hi> York <hi>was totally excluded from ever inheriting the</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown <hi>of</hi> England: He further adding, <hi>That his Lordſhip was the greateſt Oppoſer that his Highneſs had in Parliament, and that his Lordſhip never took any thing in hand (though of the greateſt moment) but he went through with it:</hi> He alſo told me, <hi>That had it not been for the Biſhops, the Bill had paſt the</hi> Houſe of Lords <hi>againſt the</hi> Duke <hi>the laſt Parliament at</hi> Weſtminſter, ſaying, <hi>That he hoped to ſee the time again, that there ſhould be no ſuch perſons as Biſhops in</hi> England; <hi>And that himſelf did not doubt but to have as good an Imploy as ever he had in a ſhort time by the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury<hi>'s means:</hi> And about that ſame time he had drawn up Papers of his own Contrivance, and went to one Mr. <hi>Combs</hi> the <hi>Coffee-man,</hi> and in my hearing deſired him to get them publiſhed; but he refuſed ſo to do; I cannot ſay, whether it was inſerted in his Papers, that which he put me upon Swearing or not; but <hi>Lewis</hi> hath ſeveral times told me, <hi>That he had urg'd him to Print the ſame in his Narrative about ſeizing the City-Treaſury:</hi> Mr. <hi>Haytor</hi> ſeveral times told me, <hi>That he was Scout-Mr.-General in</hi> Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel<hi>'s Army; and how in thoſe days perſons of good Quality came Cap in hand to him;</hi> He hath ſent ſeveral Letters to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> from the <hi>Marſhelſeas</hi> by one Mr. <hi>Hind</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Beale</hi> both Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the ſaid Priſon; the import of the ſaid Letters I knew not, but the ſaid Perſons can give a more perfect account thereof, who promiſed me the ſame upon the 17th. day of <hi>December</hi> 1681. if they ſhould be called thereunto by Authority: And this Information againſt Mr. <hi>Haytor</hi> I gave into the hands of one Mr. <hi>J</hi>— an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> at his Chamber in <hi>Cliffords-Inn</hi> about the time of the ſaid date.</p>
            <p>All this Villainous contrivance of <hi>Haytor</hi>'s was about the time of the Lord <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Tryal, at which time I being Sick, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> came to ſee me, and ſitting upon my Bed-ſide, told me, That I muſt own I knew <hi>Celier,</hi> elſe the City would not look upon me when I came abroad: <hi>For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>they are for hanging her out of the way, for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them have been with me to know if you have Sworn poſitively a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her:</hi> I ask'd Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> what made him ſo Fine? He told me, <hi>I might be as Fine if I would do as he had done?</hi> What's that, (ſaid I) Accuſe one of the Lords in the <hi>Tower</hi> as you have? <hi>Yes (by God) for nothing takes with the Parliament but ſuch things; I am now Treated, and admired by all Companies that I come into, Congratulating me with Thanks for my Service done to the</hi> Proteſtants: I told him, I was glad to hear that; and that I my ſelf wanted nothing by the Bleſſing of God, and Mr. <hi>Loman</hi>'s aſſiſtance, and others belonging to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who ſupply'd me with what I deſired, or Moneys could procure, without Imbrewing my hands in Blood, which I never had, nor would do; at which he went away in a Huff: And about a Week or a Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night before <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> 1680. Mr. <hi>John Cooms,</hi> who bought <hi>Lewis</hi>'s, and ſeveral other ſuch like <hi>Narratives,</hi> came to the <hi>Marſhalſeas,</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62262:11"/>Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> with him, where he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Coombes</hi> engaged to Mr. <hi>Loman</hi> the Keeper for what I owed him; upon which I had my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: After that time I took Lodging in the City, where I became ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſeveral Citizens at Mr. <hi>Coombs</hi>'s, and the <hi>Amſterdam Coffee-Houſes;</hi> both of them I daily frequented, and ſeveral Perſons ask'd me whether I had any Allowance from the King, according to the Addreſs made by the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> to His Majeſty on my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half: I reply'd, I had not received any: they anſwered, It was very hard meaſure; further adding, That if the King took no care of the Evidence, they knew no reaſon to the contrary, but that They might, and thought themſelves bound to do it, for thoſe who had preſerved their Lives and Liberties from the Blood-thirſty <hi>Papists.</hi> And this, or to the like effect was their common Diſcourſe in all publick places where I was amongſt them, for four or five Months together: And about the Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> told me, <hi>That he had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned another great Diſcovery;</hi> I ask'd him what it related to? he ſaid, <hi>I ſhould know as ſoon as he had fully accompliſhed it;</hi> alſo telling me, <hi>He wanted but one Witneſs to effect it, and then he could Print a Narrative that ſhould far exceed his firſt, which would be great ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Parliament, and what they had long expected to be diſcovered:</hi> He alſo ſaid, <hi>That had he an Order for the ſame, he would have it in Print with all Expedition;</hi> further declaring to me, <hi>That if he ſhould Print it without an Order, (the Preſs being free) any perſon may Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print the ſame, which would be a great loſs to him:</hi> And about a day or two after, I met with one Mr. <hi>Edward Ivy</hi> in <hi>Moor-fields,</hi> who ask'd me, <hi>Where I had been all that time he had not ſeen me?</hi> I reply'd, It was not ſo long ſince I ſaw him: <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>but you lie ſtill, and let Mr.</hi> Lewis <hi>find out all the great Diſcoveries:</hi> I deſired to know of him what new things were on foot now? At which, he told me, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Lewis <hi>had brought his Brother in to Swear that he went with great ſums of Money to Sir</hi> William Scroggs (late Lord Chief Juſtice) <hi>from the</hi> Portugal <hi>Embaſſador:</hi> I ſaid that was great Service indeed, if it were true; and ſometime after there was a <hi>Common-Councel</hi> call'd in the City, at which time ſome of the <hi>Evidence</hi> had prepared a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be preferred to the ſaid <hi>Common-Councel,</hi> to make their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion known to them of their great wants of Moneys, or to that effect, as Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> told me; I reply'd, Do you think that they will ſupply us with Money? <hi>Yes</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>thoſe that have ſigned the Petition will be ſupplyed:</hi> I ask'd him, why I was not one that ſign'd it? <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you have not made a large Diſcovery of the</hi> Popiſh Plot: And the ſame day that the <hi>Common-Councel</hi> ſat, I had Moneys before any of them; for Mr. <hi>Kidd</hi> at the <hi>Amſterdam Coffee-Houſe</hi> in <hi>Bartholomew-lane,</hi> the ſame day in <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> did ſlide a Crown into my hand; and alſo the ſame day in the ſaid <hi>Hall</hi> I ask'd <hi>Colledge</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant-Joyner,</hi> how he thought things would go? He reply'd, <hi>Very well he did not doubt;</hi> further ſaying, <hi>That he had made ſeveral of the</hi> Common-Councel <hi>of the Witneſſes ſide in order to their Supply with Moneys;</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adding, <hi>If that will not take, we will find out ſome other way to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62262:12"/>you: But</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>why do you not Swear poſitively that you know Mrs.</hi> Celier? <hi>that ſhe might be brought to a Tryal, and then you ſhall not want Moneys:</hi> All which he bid me conſider of, <hi>And I ſhould find it would be for my good:</hi> I promiſed him I would, and ſo we parted. Soon after I came acquainted with one Mr. <hi>Rowſe</hi> belonging to Sir <hi>Thomas Player,</hi> who told me, <hi>That he had undertaken to raiſe Moneys for the Supply of the</hi> Evidence <hi>until a Parliament ſhould be call'd:</hi> And upon the <hi>Tueſday</hi> in <hi>Whitſon-week</hi> 1681. I being in the <hi>Amſterdam Coffee-Houſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rowſe</hi> came to me, and deſired me to go and Drink Glaſs of Wine with Mr. <hi>Kidd</hi> and himſelf; and, to the beſt of my knowledge, there was a perſon or two with them, who were altogether ſtrangers to me; we went to the <hi>Crown Tavern</hi> behind the <hi>Royal-Exchange;</hi> where, after a little time, Mr. <hi>Rowſe</hi> gave me a <hi>Guiney,</hi> telling me withall, <hi>That that was the firſt, but ſhould not be the laſt that I ſhould have from him, if he lived and did well:</hi> And then they ask'd me many queſtions, <hi>viz. Whether I had Printed any</hi> Narrative <hi>or not?</hi> I reply'd, I had not: They ask'd me the reaſon why? I told them, it was for want of Money to get out the Copies of my Papers, that then lay in the hands of Mr. <hi>John Coombs</hi> the Coffee-man in <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew-lane;</hi> at which <hi>Rowſe</hi> and Mr. <hi>Kidd</hi> both reply'd, <hi>You ſhall not want Moneys nor Friends to aſſiſt you in this Affair:</hi> Mr. <hi>Rowſe</hi> alſo told me, <hi>That my beſt way would be to go to the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>and deſire his Lordſhips advice:</hi> They alſo deſired to know, <hi>If I had Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Duke of</hi> York <hi>or not?</hi> I told them I had; (though really I had not) at which, they reply'd, <hi>It was pity that ſuch a Diſcovery as mine ſhould lie hid, and not publiſhed for the ſatisfaction of all</hi> True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants: Then Mr. <hi>Rowſe</hi> pull'd out his Pocket-Book, and declared that he had gotten above 30 eminent Citizens to Subſcribe their Names to his ſaid Book for the Supply of the <hi>Evidence;</hi> and that ſome of them had ſubſcribed to give 20 <hi>Guineys,</hi> and ſome 30. He further declared, He did not doubt but to have as many more Hands before the <hi>Saturday</hi> night following; He again adviſing me, to go to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> concerning getting my Papers out of the hands of Mr. <hi>Coombs;</hi> and ſo for that time we parted. And ſoon after I went to the ſaid Earl's, to know how I ſhould get the Copy of my Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations out of his hands? His Lordſhip ſent me out word, <hi>That I ſhould go to Sir</hi> Thomas Player <hi>in his Honours Name, who would direct me what to do in that matter:</hi> Which accordingly I did, and coming to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Houſe, I ſent him word up that I came from the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> to him about earneſt buſineſs; upon which he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſent for me up into his Chamber, where I told him my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: <hi>He ordered me to go in his Name to Sir</hi> Robert Clayton, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire his Warrant againſt Mr.</hi> Coombs <hi>for detaining my Papers:</hi> Upon which I took leave of Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and went to Mr. <hi>Coombs</hi>'s Houſe, and demanded them: who reply'd, <hi>He had loſt them at</hi> Oxford, <hi>or coming from thence, at the time of the Parliament there;</hi> upon which I told him I had Orders from the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Player</hi> to take out Sir <hi>Robert Clayton</hi>'s Warrant againſt him: He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62262:12"/>me, <hi>He could not help it if his Life lay at ſtake;</hi> telling me, <hi>He had ſearch'd his Houſe from top to bottom, and could not find them:</hi> So I deſiſted from enquiring further after them; and ſome occaſions of my own cauſed me to go and Lodge at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> about the latter end of <hi>May</hi> 1681. where I continued for ſome weeks, and in <hi>Trinity-Term</hi> following, being in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> I met Mr. <hi>Rowſe,</hi> who came to me, and told me, <hi>He had much wondred what was become of me ſo long:</hi> I told him, that my occaſions would not permit me to ſtay in the City: He reply'd, <hi>I hope you are of the ſame Principle as when I ſaw you laſt:</hi> I anſwered, I was, and ever would be: <hi>Come then</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>we will go to the</hi> Dog-Tavern <hi>in the</hi> New-Palace-yard, <hi>and drink a Glaſs of Wine;</hi> which we did: And there he deſired me, <hi>Not to take it ill that he had queſtioned my Fidelity; for</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>it is not out of any distruſt I have of you in the leaſt, but it is becauſe you are ſo near the Court, a place that will Debauch all perſons that come near it, eſpecially thoſe that are Evidences againſt the</hi> Papiſts: At which I told him, he had no cauſe to think the leaſt ill of me in that or any other reſpect whatſoever; telling him, I had not ſpoken with any perſon belonging to the Court ſince I came laſt to lodge at that end of the Town; at which he ſeem'd very well ſatisfied; and taking Moneys out of his Pocket, gave me Ten Shillings, telling me withal, <hi>That Moneys was ſhort with him at that time, elſe he would have ſupply'd me with more; but within a few days I ſhould ſee him again;</hi> ſo we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at that time: And the ſame day that <hi>Plunket</hi> was Try'd, I met him again in <hi>Weſtminster-Hall,</hi> and we went to the ſame <hi>Tavern,</hi> where he Treated the Witneſſes againſt <hi>Pluncket</hi> after the Tryal was paſt; and return'd them many Thanks for the great ſervice they had done that day to the <hi>Protestant Party:</hi> and whilſt we tarryed there, he ſent for Mr. <hi>Rob. Squibb</hi> belonging to His Majeſties <hi>Exchequer,</hi> who accordingly came, and they went both into a Room together, but upon what bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs I know not; ſo after plenty of Wine, Evening drawing nigh, we all parted: And about three or four days after, he came to the ſame <hi>Tavern,</hi> and ſent for me; I went, where I found ſtrange Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with him, to whom he recommended me, telling them, <hi>That I was a Friend of Theirs, and all</hi> True Proteſtants, <hi>aſſuring them, that I had diſcovered a conſiderable part of a Plot contrived by the Duke of</hi> York, <hi>and other great</hi> Papiſts: Upon which they Thank'd him for bringing me into their Company, and withal call'd for Sack plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: They being upon going, Mr. <hi>Rowſe</hi> gave me other Ten Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; and told me, <hi>He would be with me very ſpeedily:</hi> And in a few days after he did come to an <hi>Ale-houſe</hi> where I frequented, and going out of the Houſe to him, he deſired me to go with him to the <hi>Fountain-Tavern</hi> in the <hi>Old-Palace-yard,</hi> where he gave me Twenty Shillings, telling me, <hi>That as ſoon as they had choſen Sheriffs in the City, and that they found they were for their turns, then they would ſettle good Allowances upon all the Evidence that ſtood by them; and that it ſhould be paid weekly until a</hi> Parliament <hi>ſat:</hi> He alſo deſired me, <hi>To come into the City again to abide with them:</hi> I reply'd, I could not, by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62262:13"/>reaſon of ſome Debts that I had Contracted there: He anſwered, <hi>Is that all?</hi> I told him it was: Then he ſaid, <hi>I ſhould not tarry long at that end of the Town:</hi> Then Mr. <hi>Rowſe</hi> took down in Writing what Sums, where, and to whom I was Indebted, telling me, <hi>That he would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pay the ſame in few days:</hi> And then he began to tell me in what a dangerous condition the <hi>Protestant Party</hi> would have been in, if the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>Evidences</hi> had not ſtood by them: <hi>For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>it is plain to be ſeen that the King is a</hi> Papiſt <hi>in his heart by his vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating that Traytor</hi> (York) <hi>his Brother, who would certainly (if it were in his power) bring us all under the yoak of</hi> Popery <hi>and</hi> Slavery: He further declared, <hi>That he hoped to ſee his</hi> Highneſs <hi>the next</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>excluded baniſhed, or both;</hi> ſaying alſo, <hi>That he deſerved to loſe his Head as much as ever</hi> Stafford <hi>did: Therefore</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him thoroughly, and I will engage you will be made for ever by it: I or</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you ſee Mr.</hi> Dangerfield <hi>lives in great Splendor, keeps his Man to wait upon him, his Gelding to ride where he pleaſes, and hath alſo</hi> 100 Guineys <hi>to command at any time; beſides, he is reſpected by the greateſt in the City, and people ſtrive to be in his Company:</hi> At which I reply'd, Mr. <hi>Rowſe,</hi> you ſee my Condition, and were I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie'd and aſſiſted as Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> is, it might be that I could do the <hi>Proteſtant Party</hi> more ſervice then ever he has done: <hi>How!</hi> (ſaid he) Yes ſaid I, for I was Bred about the Court, and have uſed it above this dozen years; and you muſt needs think; that in all this time I ſaw a great man. Intrigues: <hi>Nay</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>if it be ſo, I muſt allow you to be capable of doing us great Service; and as for your Supplies take no care, for before I am many days older, you ſhall be ſufficiently gratified;</hi> and withal took me into his Arms, and ſaid, <hi>Leave all to me;</hi> and told me, <hi>That they had a</hi> Common-Councel <hi>held in the City, and that they had made an Act how it ſhould be Engraven round the</hi> Monument <hi>in great Letters, that the</hi> Papiſts <hi>Fired this City in the year</hi> of our Lord, 1666. At which I reply'd, it was a very good Act, but withal told him, will you not be diſpleaſed at a Jeſt? He reply'd, <hi>He would not;</hi> then ſaid I. It will be a long time before the <hi>Common-Councel</hi> will make an Act, that it ſhall be Engraven in great Letters upon ſome publick place in the City, That the late King was Murthered by the Factious Party: <hi>Fie, Fie,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>thoſe things are buried in Oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; let us think of things that are to come, and what will be moſt ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for us to defend our ſelves from</hi> Popery <hi>and</hi> Arbitrary Government, <hi>which is certainly deſigned to be brought in amongſt us, elſe the King would have taken care of the</hi> Evidence <hi>that diſcovered the</hi> Popiſh Plot; <hi>But ſince He doth not, We muſt, for our own Preſervations:</hi> Theſe to the beſt of my remembrance were the very words of our Diſcourſe at that time, or to this effect: And it being towards five in the Afternoon, be told me, <hi>He was to meet ſome Eminent</hi> Citizens <hi>at ſix a Clock at the</hi> Amſterdam Coffee-Houſe, <hi>concerning raiſing Money to ſupply the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;</hi> upon which he took his leave of me, telling me, <hi>That I ſhould ſee or hear from him very ſpeedily:</hi> And the next News I heard, he was Committed to the <hi>Tower</hi> for <hi>High Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62262:13"/>
            <p>And ſome days after, which was about the latter end of <hi>June</hi> 1681. Mr. <hi>Ivy</hi> came to my Lodging in the <hi>Old-Palace-yard,</hi> and in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, began to tell me of Loyalty, <hi>And what a good thing it was to be true to the King;</hi> ſaying, <hi>He believed it lay in my Power to do His Majeſty a great deal of good ſervice, if I would diſcover what I knew:</hi> To which I reply'd, It may be I could do the King Service if I were encouraged in it; ſaid he, <hi>I do believe in my Conſcience that you know a great many Villanies and evil practices of Mr.</hi> Lewis: I anſwered, I did, <hi>Then</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>if you will go and declare the ſame before the</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State, <hi>or</hi> Committee of Councel, <hi>I dare ſay notice will be of it; for I have already diſcovered ſeveral evil practices that were acted in the</hi> City, <hi>as raiſing Moneys for the ſupply of the</hi> Evidence, <hi>and endeavouring to Suborn them, and other Treaſonable paſſages which I would no longer conceal:</hi> At that, I promiſed I would go and declare what I knew, and draw it up in writing; for that time we parted: And about a day or two after, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> came to my Chamber very much diſſatisfied, telling me, <hi>He heard that I had given in an Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation againſt him:</hi> I reply'd, I had not, (though really at that time I had finiſhed two Sheets of Paper in order to diſcover his evil practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;) but hearing ſome perſon coming up Stairs whilſt I was writing, I hid the Papers under the Bed; when he ſaw the Pen and Ink upon the Table, his great Guilt (as I imagine) caus'd him to have a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy of me, and looking in ſeveral places of the Room for Papers, yet could not find any, (Mr. <hi>Turbervile,</hi> to the beſt of my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance was with him.) To all Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s diſcourſe I made him little or no anſwer, ſo they both went their way; towards evening he came again, and declared, <hi>If I diſcovered what I knew of him, I ſhould certainly be</hi> De-Witted; <hi>but on the other ſide, if I would ſtand by him, and not diſcover what I knew againſt him, he would put me in a way to make my ſelf,</hi> telling me, <hi>that he had ſent a Letter to the</hi> King <hi>of great Moment, and that His Majeſty imparted it to no perſon but the Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>who</hi> (as he told me) <hi>had a Copy of the ſaid Letter:</hi> And ſeveral other perſwaſions he us'd to draw me off from diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what I knew againſt him; he alſo deſired me to go over the Water with him to Collonel <hi>Rich,</hi> which I did, and being there, he went and diſcourſed the Collonel at his Door for a conſiderable time, in the mean while I walk'd in the yard; the Collonel call'd me to him, and deſired me, <hi>To tell him whether I knew any thing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of what Mr.</hi> Lewis <hi>had Sworn againſt the Lord</hi> Arrundel <hi>of</hi> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor <hi>was true:</hi> I told him, I knew nothing to the contrary, becauſe I was very well ſatisfied that the Collonel was <hi>Lewis</hi>'s great Friend, therefore I did not think it convenient to declare the truth of that matter at that time, although <hi>Lewis</hi> preſt to have me Sworn we it: I leave the World to Judge why Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> ſhould perſwade me to go over, and deſire Collonel <hi>Rich</hi> to ask me the aforementioned que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, if <hi>Lewis</hi> had not been ſatisfied in his Conſcience that I knew it was all falſe, and a contrivance: Then we took leave of him, and came over the Water, where he gave me a Shilling, and told me, <hi>He
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62262:14"/>would provide me a Lodging in the</hi> City; likewiſe he ſaid, <hi>He thought it was not ſafe for me (or at leaſt himſelf,) to be at that end of the Town:</hi> Notwithſtanding, on <hi>Saturday</hi> following I went before a Committee of Lords at the <hi>Secretaries</hi> Houſe, and there declared the evil practices of Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> further giving their Lordſhips an account, that he told me I ſhould be <hi>De-Witted, if I diſcovered what I knew of him,</hi> all this Diſcourſe was in the hearing of Mr. <hi>Ivy:</hi> And finding there was little notice taken of it, by the perſwaſions of Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> I went into the City to Lodge with his Brother in <hi>Fetter-lane,</hi> where he came imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to me, and put me upon accuſing the Witneſſes that had Sworn againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> this being three or four days after his Lordſhip was laſt Committed to the <hi>Tower,</hi> deſiring me to draw up my Information with all expedition againſt Mr. <hi>Ivy;</hi> and about the ſame time brought one Captain <hi>Clynton</hi> to my Chamber, who he reported to be a great Friend of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s, and neither of them would leave me, till I had done the ſame, which was compoſed in two Sheets; the ſame Evening we took Coach, and went to the <hi>Recorders</hi> Chamber, Sir <hi>Robert Clayton</hi> being preſent, where I was Sworn, and ſeveral of the <hi>Whigs</hi> being by to ſee the ſame for their own ſatisfaction; and from thence we went to the <hi>Kings-Arms-Tavern;</hi> where they called for Wine, and laid down 6 <hi>s.</hi> more than the Reckoning for my Supply, telling me, <hi>I ſhould be better Rewarded;</hi> that Evening Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> declar'd to me, <hi>They were all perſons well affected to the</hi> Cauſe: Then I repair'd to my Chamber, where I had not long been, but Captain <hi>Clynton</hi> came, and deſired me to go to the <hi>Flower-de-luce</hi> in <hi>Fetter-lane,</hi> which I did, where he told me, <hi>That there would be a Perſon come ſpeedily to us, with</hi> 20 s. (for me) And being there for ſome time, Captain <hi>Clynton</hi> wondred at his long ſtay, and admired at it, that they ſhould be ſo Timerous, <hi>Since I had done them ſuch good ſervice that day,</hi> ſaying, <hi>He would go himſelf and ſee for the ſaid Money;</hi> which he did, and in a little time he returned to me, (not finding the perſon) but deſired me to Dine with him the next day at the ſame Houſe, which I did; there he declared to me, <hi>That he ſhould envy my Happineſs when a</hi> Parliament <hi>ſat;</hi> he likewiſe told me, <hi>That he would provide a Beeing for me at a Relations of his, where I ſhould be private until that time; and that he had a very good Horſe in Town, which, with his Perſon ſhould be at the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury<hi>'s Service, whilſt he had breath in his Body to oppoſe thoſe whom his Lordſhip did,</hi> ſaying, <hi>it was plainly to be ſeen, that the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Court <hi>deſigned to caſt the</hi> Odium <hi>of the</hi> Popiſh Plot <hi>upon the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From thence we went to the <hi>Caſtle-Tavern</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Fetter-lane,</hi> where he deſired me, <hi>To appear at o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> Old-Baily <hi>when the Bill was preferred againſt</hi> Colledge the <hi>Joyner, and there pretend my ſelf to be an</hi> Evidence <hi>for the</hi> King, <hi>by which means I ſhould be Sworn; and when I came to be examined before the</hi> Grand-Jury, <hi>I ſhould declare, that all the reſt of the Witneſſes Suborned me to Swear the ſame as they did; that it was all Falſe and Fictitious, by which means</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the Jury will bring it in</hi> Ignoramus (which it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62262:14"/>is well known they did without my aſſiſtance;) further ſaying, <hi>They expected a Bill to be preferred againſt the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>the ſame day,</hi> but there was not; further telling me, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Whitaker <hi>the</hi> Solicitor <hi>ſent him to me, and deſired him to adviſe me to what is before mentioned:</hi> The ſame day coming from the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> I met Mr. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfield</hi> going out of the <hi>Kings-Head-Tavern</hi> at <hi>Temple Bar,</hi> to whom I declar'd that the Bill againſt <hi>Colledge</hi> was found <hi>Ignoramus;</hi> to which he anſwered, <hi>I am very glad of it, for his ſake, and all perſons that have and will oppoſe the Duke of</hi> York <hi>as he hath done:</hi> The next day Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> came to my Chamber, and deſired me; <hi>To write a Letter to Mr.</hi> Wilmore, <hi>and acquaint him of my want of Moneys, and direct it to him at the</hi> Amſterdam-Coffee-Houſe, telling me, <hi>That ſince Mr.</hi> Rowſe <hi>was committed to the</hi> Tower, <hi>Mr.</hi> Willmore <hi>had undertaken to raiſe Moneys for the ſupply of thoſe Evidence that ſtood by the City:</hi> I did write, and within a day or two after, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> came with 10 <hi>s.</hi> he had of Mr. <hi>Willmore</hi> for me, which I received at ſeveral times of <hi>Lewis:</hi> And about the ſame time I told Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> I was informed that Mrs. <hi>Fitz-Harys</hi> had a great inclination to retract her Evidence againſt the Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Eſcrik;</hi> at which he ſaid, <hi>It will be good ſervice to the</hi> Whigs, <hi>if ſhe could be brought over to the</hi> City, <hi>that then he would make it his buſineſs to effect the ſame:</hi> And about a day or two after, he came again to me, <hi>That he was deſired by ſeveral Eminent</hi> Whigs <hi>to urge me to draw up my</hi> Information <hi>at large againſt Mr.</hi> Ivy, <hi>and give it in to Sir</hi> Patience Ward, who was then <hi>Lord Mayor;</hi> and by his perſwaſions I did draw up the Information, and the next day he came to my Chamber to ſee if it was finiſhed, but it was not; then he told me, <hi>That he had as good as brought over Mrs.</hi> Fitz Harys <hi>from the</hi> Court <hi>to the</hi> City, <hi>for which he had</hi> 10 l. <hi>paid him that Morning for retracting her</hi> Evidence <hi>againſt the Lord</hi> Howard; withall ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me Handſuls of Silver: I deſir'd half the Money, being the firſt that told him of any ſuch thing: he anſwered, <hi>He was forc'd to give his Bond for it, becauſe it ſhould not be thought he received it upon the account of Subornation;</hi> telling me, <hi>That the</hi> Whigs <hi>told him, that he ſhould never be call'd upon for that Money, and ſhould alſo be ſupply'd with</hi> 10 l. <hi>a Month as long as they found him True and Serviceable to them:</hi> And when my <hi>Information</hi> was finiſhed againſt Mr. <hi>Ivy,</hi> he deſired me to go with him to meet a Gentleman at the <hi>Gray-hound-Tavern</hi> near <hi>Arundel-buildings</hi> in the <hi>Strand;</hi> which I did, where there came to us one Mr. <hi>John Harrington,</hi> who afterwards appear'd to be related to me by Marriage; Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> deſired me to meet him at the <hi>Crown-Tavern</hi> behind the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> accordingly we did, but I being there before Mr. <hi>Harrington,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> call'd for Pen, Ink and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and drew up an Information againſt Mr. <hi>Ivy;</hi> Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> came in, and deſired us to go before Sir <hi>Patience Ward,</hi> and be Sworn, but I am not poſitive whether it was that day or not; but ſoon after Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> went with us, where we found Sheriff <hi>Bethel</hi> and Sheriff <hi>Corniſh:</hi> And after I was Sworn, Sheriff <hi>Bethel</hi> came to me, and gave me Thanks for the good ſervice I had
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62262:15"/>done the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at that time: Within a day or two after I met with Captain <hi>Clynton</hi> in <hi>Fetter-lane,</hi> he deſired me to go to the <hi>Golden-Lyon-Tavern;</hi> there he told me, <hi>That ſhould be the laſt time I ſhould drink with him:</hi> I ask'd to know the reaſon of it, he ſaid, <hi>He muſt be forc'd to leave the Town,</hi> declaring, <hi>That he feared Mr.</hi> Dugdale <hi>had, or would Swear againſt him:</hi> I deſired his reaſon why he thought ſo; ſaith he, <hi>Becauſe Mr.</hi> Dugdale <hi>kept correſpondence with Justice</hi> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cup, <hi>who will encourage perſons to Swear any thing against them that would appear for the</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>and eſpecially Me, for vindicating the Innocency of the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>as I have, and will ever do with my Life and Fortune:</hi> At the ſame time Captain <hi>Clynton</hi> drank the Earl's health to me in a Glaſs of Wine, telling me, <hi>What a reſpect he had me, and what a happy man I ſhould be when the Parliament ſat, until which time he hoped care would be taken for me;</hi> and then we parted, and I never ſaw him before he was brought before the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Councel,</hi> which was above a year afterwards; where I appeared, and again declared the Truth of what is above mentioned: And about this time Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> and Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> were like to fall out which of them was the chiefeſt Inſtrument in bringing over Mrs. <hi>Fitz-Harys</hi> to the City: In few days after I met Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> at the <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam-Coffee-Houſe,</hi> he ask'd me, <hi>If I never was perſwaded to Swear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury? I replyed, I was, and that the Paper that was drawn up againſt his Lordſhip, was moſt damnable and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, beſides Falſe and Fictitious, and that the Original was in the cuſtody of the Clerk of the <hi>Houſe of Commons;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>It will be good ſervice to Print it at that time;</hi> further adding, <hi>It would Incenſe the People extreamly againſt the</hi> Court <hi>Proceedings:</hi> I told him, if I had Money I would go and drink a Glaſs of Wine with Mr. <hi>Golds bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> and endeavour to get a Copy of that Paper, for which and he gave me a Crown; I went to Mr. <hi>Goldsborough</hi> at the <hi>Popes-Head-Tavern</hi> in <hi>Chancery-lane,</hi> there I deſired the Copy; he told me, <hi>He could not part with any without an Order from the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Councel, or words to that effect; upon which I deſiſted. And ſometime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I went to <hi>Oxford</hi> to <hi>Colledges</hi> Tryal, Mr. <hi>Everard</hi> came to me in the <hi>Amſterdam-Coffee Houſe,</hi> and told me, <hi>If I would give my Bond for Money, I ſhould be ſupply'd, but never call'd upon to repay the ſame;</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Bond was only that the World ſhould not take notice, or think it Subornation:</hi> I ſaid, I would give my Bond for Money, declaring that I wanted Cloaths; upon which, he ſaid, <hi>He would engage to the Taylor for a Suit for me,</hi> which he did; at the ſame time Mr. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi> deſired me to do Juſtice <hi>Warcup's</hi> buſineſs for him when an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment ſhould be brought againſt him, which he ſaid would be next <hi>Seſſions;</hi> I promiſed him I would; then ſaid he, <hi>You ſhall neither want Money nor Friends from the City, for the buſineſs is left in part to my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, for the raiſing of Money for the encouragement of the Evidence that ſtand with us:</hi> And upon the 4th. of. <hi>Auguſt</hi> Mr. <hi>Harrinton</hi> met me in <hi>Fetter-lane,</hi> and delivered me this following <hi>Subpaena.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62262:15"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="subpoena">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> John Zeal,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOu are by vertue of His Majeſties</hi> Writ of Subpaena, <hi>perſonally to appear before His Majeſties Juſtices of</hi> Goal-delivery <hi>for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of</hi> Oxford, <hi>at the City of</hi> Oxford, <hi>upon</hi> Wedneſday <hi>the</hi> 17th. day of <hi>Auguſt, about</hi> 8 <hi>of the Clock in the Morning, to teſtify the Truth between our Soveraign Lord the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Stephen Colledge, <hi>who is Indicted of certain High Treaſons in the ſaid County of</hi> Oxford: <hi>Of this you are not to fail upon pain of</hi> 100 l.</p>
                  <closer>Dated <date>
                        <hi>the 22d. of</hi> June 1681.</date>
                     <signed>On the part of <hi>Stephen Colledge,</hi> by the Court.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="subpoena">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COme to the</hi> Croſs-Keyes-Tavern <hi>in</hi> Holbourn <hi>on</hi> Munday <hi>next,</hi> by <hi>Eight of the Clock in the Morning.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>According to which I appeared, and found ſeveral perſons <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paena'd</hi> upon the ſame account, and amongſt the reſt I met with Mr. <hi>Everad</hi> and Mr. <hi>Harrington,</hi> to whom I declared, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I appear'd, I would not go in the Garb I was in; at which they reply'd, <hi>It would be much better for me to ſtay till I came back, and then I ſhould be furniſhed with all things,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That if I ſhould go to</hi> Oxford <hi>in New Cloathes, it would be thought by the</hi> Kings Party, <hi>I had them upon the account of</hi> Subornation <hi>from the City:</hi> Notwithſtanding their perſwaſions, I was fully reſolved not to go without New Cloaths; upon which Mr. <hi>Everard</hi> ſeeing my reſolution ſo fix'd; <hi>Bid me go to the</hi> Taylor, <hi>and let him bring them with all expedition ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to the ſaid</hi> Tavern; which was done, and Mr. <hi>Everard</hi> enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to pay for them; the ſame time I told Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> I wanted <hi>Linnen,</hi> upon which he went into another Room, and preſently came out again, and told me, <hi>He had got</hi> 30 s. <hi>of one Mr.</hi> Harris <hi>a</hi> Quaker; <hi>the ſame</hi> Harris (<hi>Lewis</hi> told me) <hi>ſupplyed him with the</hi> 20 l. <hi>for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over Mrs.</hi> Fitz-Harys <hi>in to the</hi> City: From thence we took Coach for <hi>Oxford,</hi> where being come, Mr. <hi>Everard</hi> came to me the night before the Tryal, and deſired me <hi>to Accuſe all the Witneſſes that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared againſt</hi> Colledge <hi>of Subornation;</hi> further ſaying, <hi>That if we could clear him, our buſineſs would be as good as accompliſhed againſt the</hi> Court <hi>Party; and when a</hi> Parliament <hi>ſits,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>no doubt but all of us ſhall have good Rewards:</hi> And that day at the Tryal, I was examined in the Court, to which I refer my ſelf to <hi>Colledges Tryal;</hi> and coming out of the Court, in the <hi>Hall,</hi> Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Hethring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> came to me, <hi>And ask'd me how it went?</hi> I told them I thought it would go very hard with the Priſoner if no body confronted Mr. <hi>Turbervile</hi>'s Evidence; at which they ask'd, <hi>Why I had not done it?</hi> I replyed, would you have me Accuſe a Perſon who I know no ill of? <hi>Yes</hi> (ſaid Doctor <hi>Oates</hi>) <hi>where a mans Life is concern'd:</hi> I reply'd,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62262:16"/>if it be your principle, it's not mine; Therefore you may do it when you are call'd in; he told me ſo he would to ſome purpoſe, without my adviſe; and after we came to <hi>London,</hi> I met Mr. <hi>Everard</hi> at <hi>Johns Coffee houſe</hi> in <hi>Bartholomew lane,</hi> where he told me, <hi>that Proviſion was making for Dyet and Lodging for thoſe Witneſſes that ſtood by the City; further telling me, that he would take particular care for my accommodation;</hi> But ſaid he, <hi>you muſt be ſure to accuſe Juſtice</hi> Warcup <hi>of Subbornation of Perjury, and the reſt of the Witneſſes that appeared on behalf of the King against the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>and thoſe of the City, when they ſhall be Indicted,</hi> which (as he ſaid) <hi>would be the next Seſſions; And then you ſhall have Money to pay all your Debts:</hi> I ask'd Mr. <hi>Everard,</hi> who was at the Charge of the ſeven or eight Coaches full of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, beſides Horſe-men that went to <hi>Oxford</hi> in behalf of <hi>Colledge?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>thoſe that were at the charge would not ſee me want, if I would accuſe the</hi> Court-Party. But about the time of <hi>Colledges,</hi> Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Brother Lodging with me, Ms. <hi>Lewis</hi> came one morning about four a clock, and called his Brother out; upon which I miſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted there was ſome new Intreigue on foot, neither could I be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied till I knew ſomething of it; within a night or two after I came in late, finding <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Brother in Bed, and in Drink, being faſt a ſleep, I treſpaſſed ſo far, as to ſearch his Pockets, where I found a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per written by <hi>William Lewis</hi>'s own hand, (as I do verily believe) which was a Recantation of his Brother <hi>Daniel Lewis</hi> for his ſwearing againſt Sir <hi>William Scroggs,</hi> which was to this effect as near as I can remember, <hi>viz That the ſaid</hi> Daniel Lewis <hi>never knew directly, or indirectly, of any Sum, or Sums of Money that was ever carried from the</hi> Portugal Embaſſador, <hi>to Sir</hi> William Scroggs, <hi>or of any thing in that nature, but that it was all falſe and fictitious, and that his Brother and</hi> Colledge <hi>the Joynor forced him to ſwear the ſame before the</hi> Recorder, <hi>they ſnatching the Paper out of his hands, and would not let him ſee what he ſwore to:</hi> The ſaid <hi>Daniel Lewis</hi> hath ſeveral times Curſed his Brother both in Bed with me, and elſewhere; telling me, <hi>his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had brought him out of a good Service, to Swear, and now will not allow him Money to ſpend,</hi> declaring to me, <hi>that he had a great mind to diſcover all that he knew against his Brother,</hi> ſaying that <hi>Sir</hi> John Moreton <hi>(whom his Brother Served) had endeavoured to take away his Brothers life for Robbing him to a conſiderable value;</hi> further adding, <hi>that the ſaid Sir</hi> John <hi>did Impriſon his Brother, and had him from</hi> London <hi>into the Countrey, but could not prove it againſt him, becauſe he had Rob'd him ſo dexterouſly.</hi> About a fortnight after I came from <hi>Oxford,</hi> I went to Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s Chamber in <hi>Black-Fryers,</hi> where he deſired me to draw up an Information to this effect: <hi>That Mr.</hi> Fitz-Gerald <hi>ſome months ſince would have perſwaded me to endeavour to bring over Mr.</hi> Smith, <hi>Mr.</hi> Dangerfield, <hi>Mr.</hi> Dugdale, <hi>Mr.</hi> Haynes, &amp;c. <hi>from the City to the Court,</hi> and by that (ſaith he) <hi>it will be all prov'd fictitious, and a Court countenance;</hi> I promiſed I would draw it up; which accordingly I did, and within a day or two I went to his Chamber, and ſhew'd him the ſaid Paper, (there being a Barber, or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62262:16"/>ſome ſuch like perſon in the Room) he read it privately to himſelf once or twice over, and (ſmilling) told me <hi>he lik'd it very well,</hi> and ſaid <hi>that it would do the buſineſs when a Parliament ſat; he deſired me to be Sworn privately to the ſame;</hi> And the Seſſions following Mr. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi> ſent me a Note, <hi>deſiring me to appear at</hi> Hicks's-Hall <hi>againſt the Witneſſes for the King, who would all be Indicted upon Subbornation of Perjury,</hi> as he inform'd me; accordingly I appeared, and that day Mr. <hi>Baldron</hi> was taken by a Conſtable, and carried into Court, from thence committed to <hi>New-Priſon, Baldron</hi> deſired me <hi>to go to the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>and acquaint them how it was with him, and deſired them to procure him Bail for his Enlargement;</hi> I accordingly at his requeſt went, where I found Mr. <hi>Everard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Harrington,</hi> and ſeveral others at Dinner in Mr. <hi>Stringers</hi> Chamber: I acquainted them of the matter, which ſtruck them into a great dump; notwithſtanding, they told me, <hi>that Bail ſhould be had immediately after Dinner;</hi> ſo I took my leave, and going down Stairs, Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> came after me, and deſired me <hi>not to declare to any perſon living where I had been, or who I ſaw together;</hi> and the next day (according to appointment) we all met at the <hi>Caſtle-Tavern</hi> without <hi>Newgate,</hi> and being at Dinner, <hi>News was brought us that Mr.</hi> Baldrone <hi>was carried before the King and Council, and had diſcovered the Intregues in the City;</hi> at which they were all at a ſtand; ſo <hi>Mr.</hi> Everard <hi>deſired us to go to the</hi> Old-Baily, <hi>and ſwear to the Indictments which were drawn up againſt Juſtice</hi> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cup, <hi>and ſeveral of the Witneſſes for the King;</hi> which accordingly we did, Sherift <hi>Bethel</hi> conducting us into Court, where one Mr. <hi>Whitton</hi> Councellor <hi>Smiths</hi> Clerk preferred the Indictments, <hi>deſiring the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes might be Sworn,</hi> but the Court rejected it; upon which the ſaid Mr. <hi>Witton,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Sangar,</hi> who belonged to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> deſired us all to go out of the Court; upon which we did, and went to the <hi>Dog-Tavern</hi> within <hi>Sudgate,</hi> where I ask'd Mr. <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> why he deſired us to come away ſo ſuddenly? he replyed, <hi>he ſaw ſome of the Kings Meſſengers in Court, and he fear'd that there might be Warrants against ſome of us;</hi> further declaring, <hi>that if we ſhould deſert them, their buſineſs would be at a great loſs,</hi> deſiring us that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared for Witneſſes, <hi>to take other Sodgings that night for fear of being ſurprized;</hi> ſo then Mr. <hi>Langar</hi> gave us Crowns a piece to lodge where we would, and alſo gave us Notes to meet at the <hi>Queens-Arms</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern in <hi>Newgate ſtreet</hi> the next morning; which accordingly we did, there the ſaid Mr. <hi>Whitton</hi> deſired me <hi>to accuſe Juſtice</hi> Warcup <hi>of Subornation of Perjury, ſo that a Bill might be preferred againſt him at the</hi> Old Baily; but that was not effected that day; Mr. <hi>Everard</hi> told me that evening, <hi>that money would be very ſppeedily produced for my ſupply,</hi> therefore deſired me <hi>not to be diſmaid, but have a little Patience;</hi> and within a day or two after, I met Sheriff <hi>Bethel</hi> coming out of the <hi>Amſterdam Coffee-houſe,</hi> who ask'd me, <hi>what News there was ſtirring?</hi> I told him all that I knew, was, that all thoſe that ſtood by the City, were ſo much ſlighted, that they had not wherewithal to ſubſiſt; he reply'd, <hi>that it ſhould be otherwiſe very ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62262:17"/>ſaying, <hi>that if I would print my Information given into the Lord</hi> Mayor, <hi>and other Papers that I could produce, I ſhould not want Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: Beſides</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it will be good ſervice to the Cauſe now in hand:</hi> I anſwered him, Sir, I know not who will ſtand by me; he ſaid, <hi>We will all ſtand by you, and I my ſelf will aſſiſt you to the utmoſt of my Power and Ability,</hi> telling me, <hi>That he himſelf was in danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sworn againſt;</hi> He alſo deſired me, <hi>To Accuſe the Lords of the Councel that I was examined before:</hi> I ask'd him what I ſhould Accuſe them of? he ſaid, <hi>Of ſuborning you to Swear againſt the</hi> Proteſtants? I told him, that I had cleared their Honours in my Information againſt Mr. <hi>Ivy;</hi> he ſaid, <hi>that was no matter,</hi> further ſaying, <hi>That the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation lay in their own hands, and that they would inſert what was moſt to their own advantage, if I would conſent thereto;</hi> he like wiſe ſaid, <hi>That there was no worſe men in the Nation to the</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>then moſt of His Majeſties</hi> Privy-Councel; further adding, <hi>That they were very odious in the eyes of a</hi> Parliament, <hi>and when one met; they would find it ſo:</hi> I told him, that I had revealed my ſelf to a Member of Parliament a week before the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was Committed to the <hi>Tower:</hi> Sheriff <hi>Bethel</hi> deſired of me to know who it was? I told him, that it was Juſtice <hi>Rich; How</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you could not have reveal'd your ſelf to a worſe man;</hi> I deſired to know the reaſon; he reply'd, <hi>That he was a great enemy to all perſons that oppoſed the Duke of</hi> York's <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt:</hi> I told him, I was very ſorry for that; he reply'd, <hi>It was very true; Therefore</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I muſt deſire you and Mr.</hi> Lewis <hi>to appear against him at the next Election of</hi> Southwark; <hi>and incenſe the People against him, ſo that he may no more be choſen to ſerve in Parliament, and I will ſtand by you upon all occaſions:</hi> About the ſame time I met with Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> at the <hi>Amsterdam-Coffee-Houſe,</hi> who told me, <hi>That it was now come to paſs, what he himſelf was put upon;</hi> I deſired to know what it was? He told me, <hi>That the King Himſelf offered him almost two years before what Money or Preferment he would deſire, if he would Swear to a</hi> Presbyterian Plot, <hi>and stand by it;</hi> I replyed, is it not enough for you to Accuſe the <hi>Duke,</hi> but you muſt Accuſe the <hi>King</hi> likewiſe; at which he anſwered <hi>(Damn me) I have my Pardon, and I will declare nothing but what a</hi> Parliament <hi>ſhall like, for it is them that will ſtand by the Evidence, and not the</hi> Court; <hi>you may plainly ſee it:</hi> And in <hi>Bartholomew-fair</hi> time, one Mr. <hi>Shewen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and my ſelf went to the <hi>Caſtle-Tavern</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> where <hi>Shewen</hi> treated us, and there declared, <hi>That he had been a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time in private with a Secretary of State;</hi> we asked upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he was there; he ſaid, <hi>For nothing as he knew, but that Sheriffe</hi> Bethel <hi>had often deſired him to ſwear that a Secretary of State would have perſwaded him to Swear againſt the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>in the City;</hi> and about the ſame time one Mr. <hi>Lune</hi> told me, <hi>That he was hired by Mr.</hi> Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, <hi>that belonged to the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>to go down to</hi> Oxford, <hi>to make proviſion for the Witneſſes that appeared for the City:</hi> And Mr. <hi>Lune</hi> hath alſo ſupply'd me with Money; and ſeveral other ſuch like practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were continually us'd in the City during my correſpondency
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62262:17"/>with them, in ſo much, that I was reſolv'd not to conceal thoſe evil practices any longer, but diſcover them in the Right of the King: And one day in my Chamber, being then drawing up an Information of what I knew, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> came in, and deſired to know what I was writing; I told him, nothing but the Intrigue of the City; <hi>Why</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>do you intend to diſcover them?</hi> I told him yes, (if I liv'd;) he reply'd, <hi>If you be ſo reſolved that you will do it, make an end of them, and let me carry them to</hi> Collonel <hi>Rich:</hi> I told him I intended he ſhould be the perſon I would be Sworn before; but through Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s great perſwaſions, I did intruſt him with my Papers, with this reſervation, that he ſhould not impart them to any of the City; upon which he wiſhed eternal damnation both to his Body and Soul if he did ſo; he went away, and in a ſhort time after he came again to me with my Papers; he ſaid, he had ſhew'd them to Collonel <hi>Rich,</hi> who ask'd him if I would Swear to them; I reply'd, I could; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that we went over the Water to a <hi>Coffee-houſe</hi> near St. <hi>Mary-overs-Church,</hi> where I writ a letter to Juſtice <hi>Reading;</hi> declaring to him, that I had matter of moment to diſcover in the behalf of the King; to which he ſent me word by Mr. <hi>Lewis, If I had any ſuch thing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, I might come to him at the</hi> Bear-Tavern <hi>at the</hi> Bridge-foot, <hi>where he then was;</hi> I went and delivered him my Information, and after he had perus'd them, he ask'd, <hi>If I could make Oath of it all?</hi> I ſaid, I could; then he adminiſtred the Oath before Collonel <hi>Rich</hi> and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Daniel;</hi> after I had Sworn, I took leave, this was about <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas</hi> 1681. from thence I went into the City, and being at the <hi>Amſterdam-Coffee-houſe,</hi> I met an Ancient Citizen, whoſe Name I knew not, he gave me half a Crown, and told me, <hi>That had not the Witneſſes deſerted the</hi> City; <hi>and gone to the</hi> Court, <hi>and diſcovered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, there had been at leaſt</hi> 10000 l. <hi>collected for the Supply of the Evidence until a Parliamen ſit; But now</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>we canot find out a ſafe way to ſupply you that are true to us:</hi> And about that time, I being late in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> drinking in a Houſe near <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> we heard Murther cryed out; upon which I went out, endeavouring to keep the Peace, the <hi>Watch</hi> and <hi>Conſtable</hi> coming in, the <hi>Conſtable</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perverſe, ſent me to the <hi>Compter</hi> for one of the Rioters; the next Morning Sherift <hi>Bethel</hi> came, and ſent for me down into the Lodge; where, (after ſome Diſcourſe,) he ordered the Keeper that I ſhould be carried before the Lord <hi>Mayor,</hi> telling them, <hi>That his Lordſhip knew me very well, and would Diſcharge me;</hi> The <hi>Conſtable</hi> came, and we went before Sir <hi>John Fredrick,</hi> who took my own Recognizance for my Appearance; after that I went to the <hi>Amſterdam-Coffee-Houſe,</hi> and deſired Mr. <hi>Kidd</hi> to pay the Fees of the <hi>Compter,</hi> which he did; and from that time I very little uſed the City: About <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> deſired me to report, <hi>That I had been with the King pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately in his</hi> Cloſet, <hi>the Earls of</hi> Arlington <hi>and</hi> Ailsbury <hi>being preſent:</hi> I asked him why he would have me report ſo falſe a thing? <hi>Piſh,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you have not a grain of Senſe, for when a Parliament ſits, you will have a good occaſion to Swear that the King and theſe Lords would
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62262:18"/>have Suborn'd you to have Sworn against the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>and ſeveral others in the</hi> City: He further deſired me, <hi>To declare the ſame to none but</hi> Whigs, <hi>and they would come in and corroborate my Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> And about <hi>May</hi> 1682. I was in Mr. <hi>Swith's</hi> Company, who ask'd me, <hi>When I ſaw Mr.</hi> Lewis? I told him, not of ſeveral days, ſaying, that he was a man that buſied himſelf in State-Affairs; at which Mr. <hi>John Smith</hi> replyed, <hi>He believed more then was juſt:</hi> I anſwered, he would have juſt cauſe to think ſo, if he knew as much as I; at which he told me, <hi>He believed it lay in my power to do the King a great deal of ſervice, to diſcover his Villanies:</hi> I ſaid, I had offered the ſame almoſt a year ſince, but little notice was taken of it; but notwithſtanding that, I would do it at any time: <hi>Lewis</hi> hath often told me, <hi>That the</hi> Queen <hi>allow'd</hi> David Firz-Gerald <hi>fourty Shillings a week;</hi> further ſaying, <hi>That her Majesty would allow any perſon elſe as much, as would come in and Accuſe the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>and thoſe in the</hi> City: And about the ſame time <hi>Lewis</hi> deſired me to report, <hi>That I had Kiſs'd the Duke of</hi> York's <hi>Hand when he came from</hi> Scotland, <hi>and when a</hi> Parliament <hi>ſits,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you ſhall ſwear that his</hi> Highneſs <hi>offered you Money to Accuſe the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>and the</hi> City; telling me, <hi>That the</hi> Duke <hi>was the only man that they aim'd at, and that I ſhould be made by Accuſing him.</hi> And about <hi>Whitſontide</hi> laſt, I had a Letter came from <hi>Lewis,</hi> to deſire me to come to him; which I did, and found him Sick in Bed; he deſired me, <hi>To go over to Collonel</hi> Rich, <hi>and tell him his Condition, and that he wanted Money:</hi> On <hi>Whitſunday</hi> I din'd with Collonel <hi>Rich,</hi> and acquainted him with what Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> had deſired me; the Collonel told me, <hi>He was very ſorry to hear he was ill, deſired to be remembred to him,</hi> and ſo took leave: I went to Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and told him what Collonel <hi>Rich</hi> ſaid; <hi>Is that all,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Lewis</hi>) I reply'd, it was that-ſignified any thing; ſays he, <hi>Is his great kindneſs come to this? Notwithſtanding he told me at his own Houſe in theſe words,</hi> viz. <hi>Mr.</hi> Lewis <hi>you and I will ſtand and fall by one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but indeed</hi> (<hi>ſaid Mr.</hi> Lewis) <hi>I muſt confeſs, that Mr.</hi> Turber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile <hi>told me before his death, that Sheriff</hi> Rich <hi>declared to him, he liked me very well, but for one thing, which was, I was too Mercinary:</hi> At which I then reply'd, <hi>You know that's true enough, you will ſell the deareſt Friend you have for Money:</hi> He anſwered, <hi>(Damn me) how can a man live without it? I urther</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Sheriff</hi> Rich <hi>was like the World, when his own turn was ſerved, he that had done him a kindneſs might hang himſelf:</hi> Saith Mr. <hi>Lewis: It's pity that by my means that the Collonel was ſo much in favour at Court:</hi> And ſometimes after I met Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> who told me, <hi>He had ſent a</hi> Porter <hi>with a Note to Collonel</hi> Rich <hi>for five Pounds, and that he could have at any time Fourty or Fifty; which</hi> 5 l. <hi>he immediately ſent him:</hi> And in <hi>July</hi> 1682. I was taken Sick at my Lodgings in <hi>Salisbury-ſtreet</hi> in the <hi>Straind,</hi> where Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> often came to me, and deſired to know of me, <hi>If Mr.</hi> John Smith <hi>had not been Tampering with me to Accuſe him;</hi> I ask'd him, if he thought all the World was like himſelf, or what reaſon he had to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect any ſuch thing? He told me the reaſon he had to believe it, was,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62262:18"/>
               <hi>Becauſe of our Intimacy, and being often together; Therefore I am ſure he hath been at you, which if you will draw up an Information againſt him, I will get you Money from the Secretary of State:</hi> I ask'd him what I ſhould draw up? He told me, <hi>That I ſhould Accuſe Mr.</hi> Smith <hi>for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to ſtifle the</hi> Popiſh-Plot; <hi>and deſiring me to Swear againſt him;</hi> I promiſed I would, not valuing what I drew up at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, acknowing him to be ſo notorious a Swearer and Suborner; I drew up the ſaid Paper which he was very well pleaſed at, only the words (<hi>detect the</hi> Popiſh Plot;) but he would have had me inſert, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Smith <hi>endeavoured to Nullifie the</hi> Popiſh Plot; but I did not after the words: Then he deſired me to write a Letter to Mr. <hi>Otter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> one of the Kings <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> and acquaint him with my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition how I wanted Money, and deſired him to make it known to the Secretary of State; <hi>Then</hi> (ſaid Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>) <hi>I'l warrant you Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi> (at that ſame time he often brought with him to my Chamber Mr. <hi>Perrea:</hi> I ſent the ſaid Letter according to his ordering, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver received any anſwer or ſupply, neither did Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> ever in the leaſt propound any immodeſt thing, but always deſired me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare nothing but what was true of any ſide: I could never be quiet at any Lodging, for Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> ſtill haunted me, being jealous of me, as I imagine: About this ſame time Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> deſired me, <hi>When I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived my Allowence from</hi> Whitehall, <hi>to pray Mr.</hi> Squibb <hi>to give me a</hi> Bill <hi>to receive it of Mr.</hi> Duncomb <hi>Goldſmith in</hi> Lumber-ſtreet: I asked him why he propoſed that? He told me, <hi>If I would conſent to it, he would carry the</hi> Bill <hi>over to the</hi> Kings Bench <hi>to one Mr.</hi> Granger, <hi>who was the Ingeniouſeſt man in</hi> England, <hi>and he ſhall Counterfeit Mr.</hi> Squibb's <hi>hand for</hi> 500 l. <hi>to be received of Mr.</hi> Duncomb, <hi>and we ſhould ſhare it amongſt us;</hi> he ſaid, <hi>that it ſhould be done ſo cleavor that it ſhould never be found out by whom it was; and that I might receive my own Money at the ſame time, and not take the leaſt notice of it:</hi> About that time I did receive a <hi>Bill</hi> from Mr. <hi>Squibb</hi> of 10 l. upon Mr. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb,</hi> which Money I received unknown to Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> for I would not have been concern'd with him in ſuch a thing for the World: Soon after our Allowances were ſtop'd, at which Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> grumbled, and ſaid, <hi>That the King made uſe of the Witneſſes as a man does of a Houſe of Eaſe, juſt for his Conveniency: Further</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they thought their buſineſs done at Court, but they are miſtaken; for I will be a greater plague to them then ever my Countrey-man</hi> Bedloe <hi>was, when a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſits; but I will have my Pardon in my hands firſt, and will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure one for you too:</hi> I ask'd him in what, he anſwered me, <hi>That We Witneſſes that had not Sworn againſt the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>ſhould Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe all them that had, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ornation of Perjury when a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſits; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhall confound their whole project; for</hi> Dugdale <hi>hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> us; and we will alſo make out, that the pretended</hi> Aſſociation <hi>that was found in the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury's <hi>Cloſet, was contrived by the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Court, <hi>and conveyed into the Earl's Cloſet by one or other of the Clerks of the</hi> Councel, <hi>by the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Courts <hi>order.</hi> That <hi>Lewis</hi> us'd to make his Brags to me,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62262:19"/>
               <hi>That all he had diſcovered againſt the</hi> City <hi>party to Sheriff</hi> Rich <hi>and others; was only under his hand, and not Sworn to,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That when a</hi> Parliament <hi>ſat he would diſcover it all, and charge it upon the</hi> Court <hi>party.</hi> I ask'd him how we ſhould go about to make it out? he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, <hi>Let me alone for that. I'll contrive it to the purpoſe:</hi> Soon after I took Lodgings in the <hi>White-Friers,</hi> where Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> came to me, and Mr. <hi>Ferrea</hi> with him, where he told me, <hi>He was to receive</hi> 50 l. <hi>and out of that he would ſupply me with</hi> 5 <hi>or</hi> 10 l. <hi>of it:</hi> And within few days after he came, and told me. <hi>That our Allowances from the</hi> King <hi>were quite taken off;</hi> and he Swore, <hi>That now it is apparent the</hi> King <hi>is a</hi> Papiſt <hi>in his heart, and ende avoured to ſtifle the</hi> Popiſh Plot, <hi>by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging the Witneſſes; and that the</hi> King <hi>endeavoured to take the</hi> Odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um <hi>from the</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and caſt it upon the</hi> Presbyterians: He alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>That the</hi> King <hi>daily endeavoured to enſlave the Nation with</hi> Popery <hi>and</hi> Arbitrary Government, <hi>and put</hi> Sheriffs <hi>and other Officers upon the</hi> City <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>contrary to Law, to ſerve his turn, and accompliſh his deſigns againſt the</hi> Presbyterians. At which I replyed, you take large meaſures of talking <hi>Treaſon;</hi> ſaid he, <hi>We that are</hi> Evidences <hi>have advantages above all other People, for we may ſpeak</hi> Treaſon, <hi>and not fear being call'd to queſtion by the Court for it; for if they ſhould take any of our Lives away, the</hi> Parliament <hi>would cenſure, that they did it on purpoſe to ſtifle our Evidence concerning the</hi> Popiſh Plot: <hi>But</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I am ſorry for Sheriff</hi> Rich, <hi>that he ſhould be made uſe of as a Tool to accompliſh their ends:</hi> Further ſaying, <hi>That Sheriff</hi> Rich <hi>had been a good Benefactor to him; but he feared he would be ſwing'd when a</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>ſat: For in a former Kings reign there were ſeveral Judges Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and he hoped to live to ſee as many Nobility and Judges go to Pot when ever a</hi> Parliament <hi>ſat;</hi> and, <hi>That his helping hand ſhould not be wanting therein.</hi> Such like Treaſonable words were the general diſcourſe he uſed in my Company, but I cannot ſay that ever any other perſon heard him talk ſo largely; neither do I know directly or indirectly what any other perſons have Sworn againſt him. About the latter end of <hi>September</hi> he told me in <hi>Salisbury-Court, That</hi> Ludlow <hi>would vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate their</hi> Charter <hi>as</hi> London <hi>did, notwithſtanding the Marqueſs of</hi> Worceſter <hi>had ſo great an Intereſt in that Town, yet he could not prevail with them to ſurrender their</hi> Charter <hi>to His Majeſty.</hi> Alſo <hi>Lewis</hi> told me, <hi>That not one in an hundred had ſigned the</hi> Addreſſes <hi>that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the King from moſt parts of the Kingdom;</hi> further ſaying, <hi>That the King could ſtand it but one Parliament more, and had it not been for the few Guards he had about him, he had been pull'd out of</hi> Whitehall <hi>long ſince;</hi> ſaying, <hi>That the late King was Dethron'd by the Sword, and This is in a fair way of being Sworn out his Throne: Therefore if you will Print your</hi> Information <hi>that is in the hands of Sir</hi> Patience Ward, <hi>and that which is in the hands of Mr.</hi> Kelley, <hi>I will engage to get you the Copies, and alſo</hi> Guineys <hi>for the Printing them, for they will incenſe the People extreamly againſt the</hi> Court; <hi>Therefore we will get them ready and publiſhed before Queen</hi> Elizabeths <hi>Birth-day, at which time the</hi> Pope <hi>is to be burnt, and there will be at leaſt</hi> 40000 <hi>People together
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62262:19"/>that night, and I will incenſe them what I can to breed a Mutiny; for he that is not blind may plainly ſee that the King is a</hi> Papiſt, <hi>or elſe he would not ſtand ſo for the Duke of</hi> York <hi>aas he has done, who is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly known to the Nation to be a grand</hi> Papiſt; <hi>And if the people did but riſe in the City, the Countrey would ſoon come in for their aſſiſtance.</hi> Further ſaying, <hi>Damn me, I am but one; get the better who can, we ſhall get employs by it.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> was very importunate with me to go into the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> (where I was born and brought up) on purpoſe to incenſe the factious ſort of people againſt the King's proceedings, and ſtir them up to a Rebellion; telling me, <hi>That he would go into</hi> Wales, <hi>and do the like there, and alſo ſupply me with moneys for my journey, in order to the ſame;</hi> But I refuſed to meddle in any ſuch matter. Moreover, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> hath divers times told me, <hi>That if ever the Court ſhould take away his life by Law, he would kill more at his death than ever he could living:</hi> I ask'd him why he ſhould fear his life being taken away, unleſs he had deſerved it? <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>there is ſtout ſwearing on all ſides:</hi> I reply'd, You know that by experience; at which he ſaid, <hi>It was as impoſſible for a man to ſwear any thing that did not pleaſe the</hi> Parliament, <hi>as it was to row a Boat through</hi> London-Bridge <hi>againſt Tide, tho' a man diſcovered nothing but the real Truth; and again, on the other ſide, if the greatest Rogue in</hi> England <hi>ſhould come in, and diſcover any thing againſt the</hi> Papiſts, <hi>though it be never ſo falſe, he ſhall be believed, and accounted an honeſt man: You may ſee it by Mr.</hi> Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bervile; <hi>when he accuſed the Lord</hi> Stafford, <hi>he was accounted a Demy-God in the City, but when he came to accuſe the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>they beſpatter'd him in a moſt odious manner.</hi> He has alſo told me, <hi>That if his Perjury ſhould be found out, he knew the worſt of it, which was but ſuffering what he had done before,</hi> (viz.) <hi>ſtand in the Pillory.</hi> Many other Treaſonable Practices I have known by <hi>Lewis,</hi> but they are too long here to inſert.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>October</hi> laſt, I was ſent for to the <hi>Greyhound-Tavern</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> where a Conſtable told me, He had a Warrant againſt me, which I willingly obey'd, (there being Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> and ſeveral in the Company, that ſaid Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> was at the ſame time committed cloſe Priſoner in the <hi>Gate-houſe;</hi>) I declar'd it was nothing but what he deſerved; And that I my ſelf deſerved Impriſonment for concealing his Treaſonable Practices; yet notwithſtanding, I told them, that if they had but ſent a Porter or Note, I would have come and declared what I knew againſt him: That night I was committed to <hi>Wood-ſtreet-Compter,</hi> where I told the Keepers, that I was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for concealing the Villainies of an ill man, and deſired them, if Sheriff <hi>Rich</hi> came there in the morning, that they would call me down to him; and he accordingly coming, ſent for me into the Lodg, asking me what I was committed for? I told him for no offence of my own that I knew of, but for concealing Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s evil Practices, which I will now no longer do. The Sheriff ask'd me if he were an evil man, or no; and whether that which he ſwore againſt the Lord <hi>Arrundel</hi> of <hi>Warder</hi> was true, or falſe? I told him it was all falſe, and that I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62262:20"/>would make it out ſo plain, that the whole World ſhould be ſatisfy'd; Upon which, Sheriff <hi>Rich</hi> departed, and preſently after I was carried before Sir <hi>William Turner,</hi> who ordered me to be carried before Major <hi>Parry</hi> at <hi>Hicks's-Hall,</hi> which was done, where the Major deſired me, that if I knew any ill of Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> I would diſcover it, or give it him in writing; which accordingly I did; Notwithſtanding which, I was committed by the ſaid Major <hi>Parry</hi> to <hi>New-Priſon,</hi> where I remained almoſt ten weeks, and at laſt was diſcharged by Law. During my Confinement there, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s <hi>Welſh</hi> Wife came to me, and told me that her Husband was inform'd I had ſworn againſt him; I declared I had not: Then ſhe reply'd, He did not fear what any perſon could do unto him, provided I ſtood his Friend; telling me, that he owned to her that his life lay in my hands; and if I could get my ſelf bail'd out, he would raiſe money for me to pay my Fees, and carry me over to <hi>Holland</hi> to the Club, (whither he adviſed me to go;) ſhe alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he would get me Letters of Recommendation to ſome perſons in <hi>Holland,</hi> by whom I ſhould be very well received; and that he alſo hoped he ſhould be with me in a ſhort time. She alſo ſaid, that ſhe had ſeveral times told him as ſhe met him in the ſtreets, that his Plotting and Contriving would bring him to the Gallows. Two or three times ſhe came, and finding nothing would work upon me, left off coming. During my Confinement, <hi>Balron</hi>'s Wife (in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of one Mrs. <hi>Thomas</hi>) came to me, and told me, <hi>Mr.</hi> Zeale, <hi>you need not tarry here a day longer; if you will but draw up an Information againſt the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>you will be ſoon fetch'd out in a Coach, and be ſupply'd with moneys.</hi> And <hi>Balron</hi> himſelf told me, <hi>That he would prove when a Parliament ſate, that the Lords in the Tower ſent Inſtructions and Dictates,</hi> how <hi>and</hi> what <hi>the Witneſses ſhould ſwear againſt the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>and others in the City.</hi> All which <hi>Balron</hi> ſaid he would ſwear, and alſo produce a Letter from-under one of the Lords hands to that effect: I ask'd him why he would ſwear it? he anſwer'd, it would be a means for him to gain the favour of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſince he was diſmiſs'd at Court. This he told me a little before I was committed to <hi>New-Priſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After my enlargement I met with Major <hi>Parrey</hi>'s Clark, (the day before <hi>Chriſtmas</hi>-day laſt) who told me, that his Maſter deſired me to go to Sheriff <hi>Rich,</hi> and give him a true account of <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Villainies; and that his Maſter had received a Letter from the ſaid Sheriff in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of <hi>Lewis.</hi> The ſame day I went; but not finding the Sheriff at his Houſe, I was directed to <hi>Fiſhmongers-hall,</hi> where I found him; He very courteouſly received me, (being glad to ſee me at liberty) and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired me to ſtay and dine with him, which I did; and at the Table I told him I came by the requeſt of Major <hi>Parrey,</hi> to give him an account of the ill practices and contrivances of Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> (there being one Mr, <hi>Stiles</hi> (as I think) at Table, who reply'd, he always took him to be a very ill man.) After ſome other diſcourſe about him, I took leave. But I had almoſt forgot one paſſage, that Sheriff <hi>Rich</hi> ask'd me if Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> had ſerved Sir <hi>John Moreton</hi> faithfully? I told him I was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62262:20"/>by his Brother, that he had Robb'd Sir <hi>John</hi> of a conſiderable value, for which he endeavoured to hang him; at which Sheriff <hi>Rich</hi> ſaid, <hi>That he did ask Sir</hi> John Moreton <hi>how</hi> Lewis <hi>behaved himſelf in his Service?</hi> (this was ask'd in the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> the ſame day Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> gave in his Information;) to which Sir <hi>John</hi> reply'd (as the Sheriff told me) <hi>That he ſerved him Faithfully:</hi> At which I replyed, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> had declared as much to me, that he ſaw Sir <hi>John</hi> in the Houſe, and that he heard him not ſpeak one word of him: <hi>For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Sir</hi> John <hi>is a great</hi> Shaftsburian, <hi>and if I diſcover'd any thing that had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Opinion, he would have beſpattered me in a moſt odious manner:</hi> And at ſeveral times I have been treated at Sheriff <hi>Rich</hi>'s Houſe, and have had Moneys from him but not upon any unjuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, neither do I know the leaſt ill by him, and he hath always ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed me to have a care of Suborners.</p>
            <p>And ſome time after, I underſtood that Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> would be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the Term following; upon which I made the beſt preparation I could, in order to receive the <hi>Bleſſed Sacrament,</hi> as may appear by my <hi>Certificate</hi> as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <p>WE the <hi>Miniſter</hi> and <hi>Church wardens</hi> of the Pariſh and Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> do hereby Certify, that <hi>John Zeale</hi> concerned in ſeveral weighty Affairs relating to His Majeſty, upon the <hi>Lords-day,</hi> common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Sunday,</hi> the 14th. day of <hi>February,</hi> immediately after <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service</hi> and <hi>Sermon,</hi> did, in the Pariſh-Church aforeſaid, receive the <hi>Sacrament of the Lords Supper</hi> according to the uſage of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> In witneſs whereof we have hereunto ſubſcribed our Hands the 4th. day of <hi>February,</hi> in the year of our Lord, <hi>1682/3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Bartholomew Wormell</hi> Miniſter of the Pariſh and Pariſh-Church aforeſaid.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Giles Burrows</hi> Church-Warden of the ſaid Pariſh and Pariſh-Church.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALexander Harris</hi> Gent. and <hi>John Harris</hi> Victualler, both of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> do ſeverally make Oath, that they do know <hi>John Zeale</hi> in the above-written Certificate named, and who now preſent hath delivered the ſame into this Court; and do further ſeverally make Oath, that they did ſee the ſaid <hi>John Zeale</hi> receive the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> in the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Margaret Weſtminſter</hi> aforeſaid, in the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate mentioned, and upon the day, and at the time in the ſaid Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in that behalf certified and expreſſed: And that they did ſee the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate above-written Subſcribed by the ſaid <hi>Miniſter</hi> and <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Alexander Harris.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Harris.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62262:21"/>
            <p>And upon the ſame day I received a <hi>Subpaena</hi> to appear the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="subpoena">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Mr. <hi>John Zeale,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BY vertue of His Majeſties Writ of <hi>Subpaena</hi> to you directed, you are to appear before our Soveraign Lord the King at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> on <hi>Monday</hi> next after the eight days of the <hi>Purification</hi> of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> to teſtify the Truth, and give Evidence againſt <hi>William Lewis,</hi> for certain Treſpaſſes, Contempts and Miſdemeanors: And this you muſt not omit under the Penalty of <hi>100 l.</hi> to be levyed on your Goods and Chattels, if you make default.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 
                        <date>the 4th. day of <hi>February 1682/3.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>According to which I did appear, and being Sworn in Court, I gave in my Evidence to the <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi> where the Bill was found, and ſoon after I received another <hi>Subpaena,</hi> which is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="subpoena">
               <body>
                  <p>THeſe are in His Majeſties Name to command you perſonally to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before Sir <hi>Edmund Saunders</hi> Knight, Lord Chief Juſtice of His Majeſties Court of <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 13th. of this inſtant <hi>February,</hi> at <hi>8</hi> of the Clock in the Forenoon, at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall,</hi> to teſtify the Truth on the behalf of our Soveraign Lord the King, againſt <hi>William Lewis,</hi> for certain great miſdemeanors whereof he ſtands Indicted; and hereof you are not to fail, on the Penalty of <hi>100 l.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Dated <date>the <hi>8th.</hi> day of <hi>February,</hi> in the 35th. of the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </date>
                     <signed>Aſtrey:</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I alſo appeared to this, but Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> deferred his his Tryal till next term following; and upon the 6th of <hi>March</hi> 1682/3. I was at the <hi>Naked-Boy</hi> in the <hi>Old-Pallace-yard Westminſter,</hi> in Company with Mr. <hi>Ambroſe Kelley,</hi> one of the Clerks of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> who told me, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Lewis <hi>was with him, to deſire the Copy of a Paper that was in his Cuſtody,</hi> which ſaid Paper was that which Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> chiefly contrived himſelf, and would have had me to have Sworn to it againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> and it was alſo the ſame Paper that was contrived by him in the <hi>Marſhalſeas;</hi> Mr. <hi>Kelley</hi> further ſaith, that Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> told him, <hi>That he came from me, and alſo offered him a good Gratuity for the ſaid Copy;</hi> further telling the ſaid Mr. <hi>Kelly, That it would be a means for him to Ingratiate himſelf into the favour of a</hi> Whiggiſh <hi>Parliament.</hi> But for all his offers and perſwaſions, Mr. <hi>Kelley</hi> refuſed to give him the Copy; This Mr. <hi>Kelly</hi> Confeſs'd before one Mr. <hi>Alexander Harris,</hi> and ſeveral others.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62262:21"/>
            <p>And in <hi>May</hi> laſt I received another <hi>Subpaena,</hi> to which I alſo Appeared.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="subpoena">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Mr. <hi>John Zeale,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THeſe are in His Majeſties Name to command you perſonally to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before Sir <hi>Edmund Saunders</hi> Knight, Lord Chief Juſtice of His Majeſties Court of <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the ninth of this Inſtant <hi>May</hi> at one of the Clock in the Afternoon at <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> to teſtify the Truth on the behalf of our Soveraign Lord the King, againſt <hi>William Lewis,</hi> for certain great miſdemeanors whereof he ſtands Indicted; and hereof you are not to fail, on the Penalty of <hi>100 l.</hi> to be levyed on your Goods and Cahttels.</p>
                  <closer>Dated <date>the 2d. day of <hi>May</hi> in the 35th. of the King,</date>
                     <signed>Aſtrey.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And being Sworn in Court I gave in my Evidence, and upon a full hearing on both ſides, Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> was brought in guilty of theſe words following, which were in his Indictment, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="indictment">
               <body>
                  <p>TThat the King is a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and endeavours to ſtifle the <hi>Plot,</hi> by Dicharging of the Witneſſes. And that the King endeavoured to take the Odium from the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and caſt it upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> And that the King and Court put the Paper of <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> which was found in the ſaid Earl's <hi>Cloſet,</hi> upon the ſaid Earl. And that the Paper was conveyed into the ſaid Earl's <hi>Cloſet</hi> by Mr. <hi>Gywn</hi> by the Order of the King and Court. And that the King did daily endeavour to enſlave the Nation with <hi>Popery.</hi> And put <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and other Officers upon the City of <hi>London</hi> to ſerve Turns, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his Deſigns againſt the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I cannot omit one remarkable Paſſage of Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> which was about the time of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Commitment laſt to the <hi>Tower,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> told me, <hi>That whenever a Parliament ſat, that he would diſcover ſuch things as ſhould make all</hi> Europe <hi>ſtand amazed, but he would have his Pardon firſt in his hands:</hi> I deſired to know why he declared himſelf in that manner; he replyed, <hi>That he had been at</hi> Hampton-Court <hi>with the King, Mr.</hi> Turbervile <hi>being then with him, who made ſome Diſcovery;</hi> why ſaid I, did you hear any of what was ſaid; no ſaid he, <hi>But I ſaw thoſe that ſhall come in for a ſnak the next Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He the ſaid <hi>Lewis</hi> has ſeveral times told me, <hi>That if the King would give ſuch encouragements, as Pardons and Allowances, that His Majeſty ſhould not want New Evidence, and Freſh Diſcoveries, as long as he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62262:22"/>lived;</hi> further ſaying, <hi>That the Goals in and about Town, were the Nurſeries for ſuch Supplies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame day I was Sworn in the <hi>Speakers Chamber</hi> by order of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> on the 19th. day of <hi>November</hi> 1680. as it will appear by the <hi>Votes</hi> of that day: There came up ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and deſired of me, <hi>If I could not call to mind the</hi> Duke's <hi>coming to the Crown ſuddenly:</hi> Which in my apprehenſion was putting men in mind what they would have them to Swear: But I do declare, that I never ſpoke one word to his <hi>Royal Highneſs</hi> in my life, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I have been put upon ſo often to Accuſe him.</p>
            <p>And before the laſt <hi>Dutch-War</hi> I was preferred to Sir <hi>George Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> as one of his Pages, who then went Ambaſſador to <hi>Holland;</hi> for which I had his Certificate, which is as followeth <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <date>March <hi>the</hi> 3d. 1672/3</date>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THeſe are to Certify whom it may concern, that Mr.</hi> John Zeale <hi>ſerved me Faithfully as a Page, during my late Embaſſage in</hi> Holland.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>George Downing.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <div type="depositions">
               <head>The Teſtimonies of ſeveral Credible Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in the Confirmation of many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Occurrences mentioned in this <hi>Narrative.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="deposition">
                  <head>The Confirmation of Mr. <hi>William Banks.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MR. Zeale <hi>came one day to my Houſe and told me,</hi> That there were ſome perſon or perſons that were Tampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with him to give Evidence againſt Sir <hi>Francis Radcliffe</hi> of <hi>High Treaſon;</hi> and that he was to have a ſum of Money for the ſame: <hi>Beſides he deſired me,</hi> To inform Sir <hi>Francis</hi> of the ſame, <hi>which I did. This is the whole Truth, and nothing but Truth, as witneſs my Hand, and that it was about the time Sir</hi> Francis <hi>was laſt in Town.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>William Banks.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62262:22"/>
               <div type="deposition">
                  <head>The Confirmation of Mr. <hi>John Smith.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AT the Requeſt of Mr.</hi> John Zeale, <hi>I do herein declare, that the ſaid</hi> Zeale <hi>about two years agoe told me,</hi> That one <hi>William Lewis,</hi> who was a Priſoner in the <hi>Marſhalſea,</hi> and at <hi>Newgate;</hi> Pillored and Burned in the Hand, for his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Exploits, was the worſt of men to his knowledge; which he in time would convince the World of his Wicked and Treacherous Practices: <hi>adding,</hi> That he verily believ'd, the ſaid <hi>Lewis</hi> exceeded all mankind in Villany and wicked Contrivances againſt the King's Intereſt. <hi>The ſaid</hi> Zeale <hi>alſo told me; in the preſence of Juſtice</hi> Warcup, <hi>Mr.</hi> John Macknamarra, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Stephen Dugdale, That the ſaid <hi>William Lewis,</hi> when he was a Priſoner in the <hi>Marſhalſea,</hi> (taking upon him the Title of Lord <hi>Chancellor</hi>) there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and framed a moſt horrid Deſign againſt the Lord <hi>Arundel of Warder, viz.</hi> How the ſaid Lord would Suborn him to Swear many things againſt the Kings Intereſt; <hi>and alſo,</hi> Engage him to Murder the King, for which he was to have 1500 <hi>l.</hi> from the ſaid Lord <hi>Arundel. The ſaid</hi> Zeale <hi>alſo told me,</hi> How the aforeſaid <hi>Lewis</hi> prevailed with his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was a Footman to the <hi>Portugal</hi> Embaſſador, to Swear againſt the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Screggs,</hi> that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſeveral Thouſands of <hi>Guineys</hi> from the aforeſaid <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> to ſave Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi>'s Life; and that to his knowledge the ſaid <hi>Lewis</hi> had a Penſion from the <hi>City,</hi> for giving them Intelligence of what he could learn at <hi>Court,</hi> though at the ſame time he pretended to Inform the <hi>Court</hi> of what paſſed in the <hi>City. All this Mr.</hi> Zeale <hi>told me in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of many.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Smith.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="deposition">
                  <head>The Confirmation of Mr. <hi>Robert Elmes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Robert Elmes <hi>doth declare, That upon the third day of</hi> Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary <hi>laſt paſt, being at the</hi> Bufflers-head-Tavern <hi>near the</hi> Gate-houſe Weſtminſter, John Hankyſon <hi>one of the</hi> Turn-Keys
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62262:23"/>
                     <hi>of the ſaid Priſon, brought one Mr.</hi> Lewis <hi>to me, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired me,</hi> To go and Arreſt a perſon, who was then at the St. <hi>Johns-head-Tavern,</hi> commonly called <hi>Heaven</hi> in the <hi>Old-Pallace-yard: I demanded of the ſaid</hi> Lewis, <hi>if he had any Writ or Warrant againſt him, whether it was his own Debt, or not, he anſwered,</hi> No, <hi>telling me,</hi> Any piece of Paper will afright him, and if I would undertake it, he would give me a good Gratuity: <hi>The ſaid</hi> Turn-key <hi>alſo perſwaded me to undertake it, telling me,</hi> That he was a Friend of his, and would not put any thing upon me, but what he would bear him out in, <hi>or to that effect: I ask'd the Perſons Name whom they would have Arreſted; they told me,</hi> One Mr. <hi>John Zeale, (a perſon who I never ſaw in my life to my knowledge till that time:) I told them I would not undertake it, aſſuring them that I never did any thing in that nature without a Lawful Warrant, neither would I then begin: And finding nothing would prevail upon me, they departed; I perceived it was a piece of Malice and Roguery, I ſent my Man to the ſaid St.</hi> Johns-head Tavern, <hi>to acquaint the above-mentioned Mr.</hi> Zeale <hi>of the deſign there was againſt him, leaſt any other Officer ſhould undertake it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Robert Elmes.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="deposition">
                  <head>The Confirmation of Mr. <hi>John Harris.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ON the</hi> 23d. <hi>day of</hi> March 1682/3 <hi>Mr.</hi> John Zeale <hi>being very ſick, and not expecting to live, he ſent for me, and told me,</hi> He did not know whether he ſhould live or die, and deſired me, if it ſhould pleaſe God to take him out of the World, that the Papers which he did intend to publiſh, was all true, as he might anſwer before the great God. <hi>He alſo deſired me to get them printed, to ſatisfie the World what Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guery there has been acted I told him,</hi> That it was a Juſtice of Peace's buſineſs; and if he thought convenient, I would go to one, and get him to come and give him his Oath; but he recovered of that Sickneſs, which prevented my bringing a Juſtice of the Peace to him. <hi>All which I am ready to make Oath, if it ſhall be required.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Harris.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62262:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
